<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The exercise of armes for caliures, muskettes, and pikes after the ordre of his Excellence. Maurits Prince of Orange Counte of Nassau etc. Gouernour and Captaine generall. ouer Geldreland. Holland, Zeeland, Vtrecht. Overyssel. etc. Sett forthe in figures. by Iacob de Gheyn. With written instructions. for the service of all captaines and comaundours. For to shewe hereout the better vnto their jong or vntrayned souldiers the playne and perfett maner to handle these armes.</title>
            <title>Wapen-handelinghe van roers, musquetten, en spiessen. English</title>
            <author>Gheyn, Jacob de, 1565-1629.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1608</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 108 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 135 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01673</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11810</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S122015</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99857168</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99857168</idno>
            <idno type="VID">22852</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01673)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 22852)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1237:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The exercise of armes for caliures, muskettes, and pikes after the ordre of his Excellence. Maurits Prince of Orange Counte of Nassau etc. Gouernour and Captaine generall. ouer Geldreland. Holland, Zeeland, Vtrecht. Overyssel. etc. Sett forthe in figures. by Iacob de Gheyn. With written instructions. for the service of all captaines and comaundours. For to shewe hereout the better vnto their jong or vntrayned souldiers the playne and perfett maner to handle these armes.</title>
                  <title>Wapen-handelinghe van roers, musquetten, en spiessen. English</title>
                  <author>Gheyn, Jacob de, 1565-1629.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[20] p., 42, [43], 32 plates   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>They are toe bye at Amsterdam by Robert de Baudous. 1608. Printed at the Hage. With priviledge of the Emperours Matie. the King of Fraunce, and the noble and mightye Estates General of the vnited Provinces,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[The Hague] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1608]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Gheyn, Jacob de.  Wapen-handelinghe van roers, musquetten, en spiessen.</note>
                  <note>The title page is engraved, with compartments left blank for three English pasted-on engraved labels: (1) arms of Henry, later Prince of Wales, (2) title (see next note for variant), and (3) imprint. Title page variant 1: dated 1607. Title variant 2: dated 1608, but blank spaces now engraved with the arms of Maurice, Prince of Orange (shield with bugles and lions rampant); title in French ("Maniement d'armes d'arquebuses, mousquetz, et piques"); imprint "Imprimé a Amsterdam chez Robert de Badous .."; Latin dedication to Maurice ("Illustrissimo principi, maximo duci, Mauritio Nassauio .."), ending with "On les vend' ausi a Amsterdam chez H. Laurens". Variant 3: like variant 2, but lacking the words "On les vend' ..".</note>
                  <note>Pasted-on title label variant 1: lacks the line "They are toe bye ..".</note>
                  <note>This edition has nine leaves of English letterpress: dedication is on pi¹; preface is on ([three stars])¹; A-B¹ contain directions for the caliver; A-B¹ (signed in italic) contain directions for the musket; a-b¹ [c]¹ contain directions for the pike.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Military art and science --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Weapons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Armor --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:22852:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:22852:1"/>
            <p>THE EXERCISE OF ARMES FOR <hi>GALIVRES, MVSKETTES, AND PIKES</hi> After the ordre of his Excellence. Maurits Prince of Orange Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te of Naſſau etc. Gouernour and Captaine generall. ouer Geldreland. Holland Zee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land Vtrecht. Overyſſel. etc.</p>
            <p>Sett forthe in figures. by Iacob de Gheyn.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>With written Inſtructions for the service of all Captaines and Comaundours. For to shewe hereout the better vnto their jong or vntrayned Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers the playne and perfett maner to handle these Armes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed at the Hage. With Priviledge of the Emperours Ma<hi rend="sup">tie</hi>. the King of Fraunce, and the Noble and migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye Estates General of the vnited Provinces</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:22852:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:22852:2"/>
            <head>TO THE PRINCE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Or your highnes, nor any man to vvhoſe vevv this preſent booke ſhall come, ſhall need to finde it ſtrange, either, vvhy it hath borrovved an Engliſh habitt, or ſhrovvded it ſelfe vnder ſo great a protection: ſince on the one ſide it repreſents vnto You that manner of exerciſe of Armes, vvhich hath for many yeares bene practiſed in this ſchoole of vvarre, the Vnited Provinces, and that, by a Captayne vvhoſe vvorth (I thinke) not any part of the vvorld is ignorant of: in vvhich vvarre the valure of the Engliſh and Schottiſh nations (novv Brittaynes) hath bene of that ſpeciall marke and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, that, for readye vſe of theyr Armes, prouident care of the Commaunders and commendable obedience of the Souldier tovvards his chiefe, it can not be denyed but that the Provinces haue received verye acceptable ſervices at theyr handes. On the other ſide: to vvhom could I (in iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement) more fitly and (as I may ſaye) iuſtly, addreſſe the proprietye of a vvorke of this vvorthe and nature? then to a <hi>Prince</hi> deſcended from ſo many povverfull and victorious Kinges, vvho euen by deſtyny and iudgement of all the vvorld, is not onely the heyre of theyr Fortunes, but an inheritour of theyr vertues alſo: then to a <hi>Prince</hi> the ſonne of the moſt puiſſant Kinge of all his predeceſſours: vvho, though he bleſſeth his Realmes vvith the ſvveeteneſſe of peace, yet (doubteleſſe) he placeth the ſecuritie of that content, in the due and lavvfull exerciſe of Armes. Laſtely, to vvhom rather (I ſaye) ſhould I dedicate this vvorke? then to a <hi>Prince,</hi> that through the light of his ovvne proper example, doth ſo much beautifye and ennoble the practiſe of Armes, vvho euen in the fore-ſpringe of his yeares and amidſt ſo many other princely entertaynements fitt for his youth and ſtate, doth yet give ſuch a luſtre to this of Armes, by the continuall fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaritye he hath vvith them in his often practiſe, that I thinke I may ſaye, and ſaye truely, that the moſt true and perfect knovvledge of them is rather to be found vvith your Highnes, then brought to You. Therefore, as all thoſe excellent profeſſours of excellent ſciences (vvhere in yet your Highnes excells them all) are every one in ſpeciall duety bound, to giue the beſt teſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monye they can of theyr thankefulneſſe, both in regard of the fauour vvhich ſome receive in being nere You, and alſo of the honour vvhich You doe to all theyr profeſſions, in not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayninge to participate vvith theyr induſtries: So haue I in all humble and due reſpect, thought it fitt, to tender You this acknovvledgement of myne, hopinge that your Highnes ſhall receive no ſmall contentement, by addinge the longe experience of the Nether-lands practiſe to Your ovvne knovvledge of ancient Hiſtories, and thoſe vviſe and deep-grounded inſtructions of that great Monarche the Kinge Your Father.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Highnes his.</hi> Moſt humble ſervant in all duetye at command. Iacob de Gheyn.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:22852:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:22852:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THOSE THAT LOVE THE EXERCISE OF ARMES WISSHETH IACOB DE GHEYN HEALTH and proſperitie.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is out of all doubt, that neither the quietneſse of a common wealthe without armes, nor the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes without convenient or due exerciſe, can ſtand or be maintained. VVhich hath not onely bene well conſidered by the old ſages or wiſe, that haue vndertaken to give any examples of lawe, but is approoued by the effectuall experience of the most famous Townes and People, that haue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved their Estate chieflye by thoſe meanes. And examining the further courſe of the whole VVorld, we ſhall find, that the ſoueraigne powre hath alwayes bene by thoſe which here in did moſt ſurpaſſe theyr neighbours. The Grecians, in the time thye haue bene in theyr most ſhyning glorie haue much embraced this point, and there in by theyr witt not little proffited. Yet the Romains haue farre ſurpaſsed here in aſwell thoſe as all others, and ever exerciſed theyr youth at all kinde of armes by thoſe whom they called Campi-doctores or Mastres of the field. VVhich maner is playnelye ſhowed vnto vs, in the writinges that are there of come to our handes, the ſame reaſon standeth fast for euer, and with all nations. But in regard that not onely the vſe but euen the armes them ſelues are much changed chiefly ſithence the findinge out of Gun pouder, it can not be denied but that wee can reape ſmall or no benefite by the old rehearſals, without wee haue neewe instructions. His Princely Ex<hi rend="sup">ce</hi>. there fore the Earle <hi>Maurice</hi> of Naſsau &amp;c. to whoſe care (by the Lords Estates generall of the vnited Provinces) is left the charge of defending ſo worthie countries and the conducting of a warre which is taken for a ſchoole or patterne to the whole VVorld, Like as he throughout the whole militarie order (before his time, much decayed) hath restored and partelye brought to the examples of the old, partely by his owne inventions amended and adorned, ſo hath he taken great regard to the exerciſe of Armes, as one of the principall partes of the militarie ordre, where out are riſen ſuch comodites as vnto euery man is knowne not onely in theſe Countries but alſo in the vttermoſt partes of the worlde. This hath bene the chiefe cauſe that hath mooved me to giue out the order which his Princely Ex<hi rend="sup">ce</hi>. in the vſing of the Calivres, Muſkets and Pikes doth obſerue as the perfecteſt and best patterne, aſwell to pleaſure thoſe whoſe duety it is to followe the order of his directions, as to accomo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date any other who ſhall ſeeke to draw benefytt to hymſelf by ſo neceſſary exerciſe and practiſe of armes. Having to that purpoſe drawne all the poſtures that come in the holding or vſing of the armes by order and the ſame deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribed with his reaſons and wordes of comand: A worke (without queſtion) very fitt for novices and yongeſo ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers to whom it belongeth to exerciſe themſelues with great diligence here in, verye neceſſarye alſo to all Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynes and Comandors the better to looke to the exerciſing of ſouldiers, and laſtly verie proffitable to all Princes and People, beit in tyme of warre the better to defend themſelues, and offend theyr ennemyes or be it in time of peace with the more facilitye (by this kinde of exerciſing) to draw a better aſsurance to themſelues, and become the more dread full and redoubted to others. Seening then our meaning goeth no further then to inſtruct the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trained ſouldiers and to reinforce the minde of the expert by the ſight and reading of it: No man ſhall finde it ſtrange that wee in drawing of the Pikes, onely ſet that which for the vſe of the ſame is moſt neceſſarye, omitting diverſe maners of toſsing of the pike by forme of recreation, which in militarie exerciſe bringeth little benefite or profite. Concerning the different or ſutable apparell and armes of the figures, there is to be conſidered, that the ſhott with head peeces, and the Muſkettiers with hattes are drawne and differently appareled, not that we hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de it for neceſsarie, but that ſuch varietye might give the fuller ornament to the pictures, and to ſhowe to poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie the manner of ſouldiers apparel vſed in theſe dayes, Like as on the other ſide the Pikemen are all armed after oneſorte or kinde, for no other reaſon then to repreſent the right maner and faſhon of the arminge of his Ex<hi rend="sup">ces</hi>. owne Garde, as it is at this tyme. In the ſmall ſhot and Muſquettiers, you ſhall alſo conſider that the firſt figure ſhoweth how a man ſhall holde a Muſket or Caliver already charged vpon his ſhoulder, and the other pictures followinge tell what is further to be done bothe for diſcharging, and lykewyſe for charging againe of the peece. And becauſe that every man ſtanding ſtill ſhall knowe how to behaue himſelf intyme of need, there is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly
<pb facs="tcp:22852:4"/>
ſet downe in the ende ech ſeuerall picture with his ſeuerall difference of stand or posture and that to give truer light to the iudgement of the obſeruer. But aboue all is to be well conſidered that which ſeemes here to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire a leaſurly and ſtow proceeding in the apprehenſion (by reaſon of the ſmalenes of the ſculpture which could not conveniently be otherwiſe formed) that I ſay) must the induſtrious learner with a diligent practiſe strive to bringe to a nimble and quicke readines of action. Neuertheleſse ſo, as that in the beſt faſhon and with the most care and providence he make it appear that it is to offend the ennemy without hurting or anoynig him ſelf or his fellowe, the rest the written instructions and the pictures ſhall ſhewe.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <div xml:lang="eng" type="version">
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:4"/>
               <head>SHORTE INSTRVC<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION VPONTHE CONTREFAIC TINGES, TOVCHING THE RIGHT VSE OF CALIVERS, for the yonge or inexpert Shot, vvhich inſtruction by Cypher letters is agreeing or an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſvvering orderly vvith every picture. And becauſe here to are ioyned ſome pictures of ſtanding ſtill for ſentenels, to ſhevv hovv the ſouldier in tyme of need (readie vvith his pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce) ſhall ſtand, there fore doe the vvritinges alſo there of agree vvith every figure or picture, according his number.</head>
               <head type="sub">SHOT.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt of al is in this figure ſhovved to euery Shot hovv he ſhall ſtand and Marche vvell, and alſo hold and carye his Caliver, Matche and Rapier: That is to ſay, he ſhall in laying on the peece ioyne the Seer cloſe to the ſhoulder, holding it vvith the left hand, and that about the hollovve or thumb-hole of the ſtock, and not at the end there of, remembring alvvayes to cary it vvith the mouth vp, leaſt if by chaunce the peece vvent of, he ſhould hurt his fello<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vve, he ſhall alſo hold the match burning or kindled at bothe the endes, betvvixt the tvvo leaſt fingers of the ſame left hand, holding the ſame hanging dovvnevvards vvithin the ſtock, to the end that he may lenghthen the ſame at all tymes, and to vſe and change one end after an other, ſhall alſo beſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des his flaſke or charges, carye about him a tutchboxe vvith tutch pouder, to put out of the ſame and not out of the flaſke or charges, the ſayd pouder in to the pan.</p>
               <p>In the 2. figure is taught, hovv he going and preparing him ſelf to ſhoote, ſhall take the peece from the neck, that is to ſay, he ſhall not vvith the left hand pull the peece from the ſhoulder, but ſhall take it vvith the right hand onely (like as this figure ſhevveth) beyond the great ſkrue, becauſe the peece fals there, (benig ballanced in the hand) much lighter, and ſhall take it of vvith one hand alone (vvhereby ſhall be ſene that he is mayſter of his peece) ſinking it a little in the left hand vvithout bending or hanging his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye tovvards it.</p>
               <p>In the 3, hovv he ſhall hold and gouerne the peece before he take it in the left hand, he ſhall vvith the right hand hold the peece in ballance, vvith the mouth vpvvards, vvithout tutching the bodye, and haue readie the left hand to meete the peece and to receauce it in the ſame.</p>
               <p>In the 4. hovv he ſhall carye the peece in the left hand, ſtanding and going, not onely eaſely and vvell, but alſo hold it in ballance in the ſame hand, that it doe not lye to high nor to lovv, and alſo not hurt his fellovve if the peece vvent of by chaunce, ſetting for eaſe and ſuretye ſake the elbovv againſt his hyppe, like as this figure teatcheth.</p>
               <p>In the 5. hovv he ſhall vvell and proprelye take the match out of the left hand vvith the tumb and ſecond finger holding alvvayes the peece in a due hight, aſvvell for the eaſe, as for not to hurt his fellovve vnad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſedlye, and although that generally (for ſome good reſpects) vve have ordayned to take the matche bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvixt the thumb and ſecond finger, yet is it not our purpoſe ſo preciſely to binde a man thereto, as that he maye not take the ſame betvvixt the thumb and tvvo next fingers, if that be eaſier for him.</p>
               <p>In the 6. hovv he ſhall blovv of the match and hold it vvel betvvixt the thumb and ſecond finger, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he do put it vpon the Cock, that is to ſaye, he ſhall bring the match handſomely neare the mouth, and blovv of the ſame vnder the hand, vvithout bending himſelf to much thereto, like as this figure ſhevveth.</p>
               <p>In the 7. hovv he ſhall vvith the thumb and the ſecond finger, bring the match into the Cock, and not ſkrue it in, for to looſe no tyme and is te be vnderſtood, that he alvvayes a fore hand, ſhall direct the vvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deneſſe of the Cock to the thickneſſe of the match, for to be the ſooner readie to ſhoote.</p>
               <p>In the 8. hovv he ſhall hanſomly trye his matche and vvith the thum and ſecond finger gouerne the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, to the end he may make it preſently longer, ſhorter, as alſo higher, and ſo ſet the ſame that the peece do not faile or refuſe him.</p>
               <p>In the 9. hovv he ſhall blovv of the match ſpeedely and vvell, and being vvell blovvne of, finely vvith open armes and vvith the tvvo fore fingers couer the pan lid for the ſparkes, and ſhall open the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:22852:5"/>
vvithout bending him ſelff tovvards it, bringing handſomely the peece to his mouth, like as this figure ſhevveth.</p>
               <p>In the 10. hovv he ſhall preſent the peece, from aboue dovvnevvards, and not from beneath opvvards, to the ende he doe no harme te his fellovve, that goeth a fore him, (if by chaunce the peece vvent of) and alſo that the bullet that can not alvvayes (eſpecially in tyme of haſte) be rammed in do not fall out.</p>
               <p>In the 11. hovv he ſhall ſet the peece againſt his breſt and preſent it, bovve his head, hold vp the right elbovv, and ſtand right and faſt vvith his bodye, and becauſe the peece ſhall be ſet againſt the breſt and not againſt the ſhoulder, ſhall ſet the bodye to it: moreouer hovv he ſhall bovv in the knee the left legge, that muſt ſtand before, and hold ſtyf and ſtrong the right, legge that muſt ſtand behind, to the end he may bothe the better gouerne and diſcharge his peece, as alſo accomodate, him ſelfe in the preſentinge of it.</p>
               <p>In the 12. hovv he ſhall (having ſhott) take the peece oderly from his cheeke, and hold it vp leaſt he ſhould hurt his fellovve if the peece (fayled before) ſhould chaunce then vnavvares to goe of.</p>
               <p>In the 13. hovv vvith the ſame fingers vvhere vvith he ſet the match in the cock, he ſhall handſomely take it againe avvaye, not pluckinge or tvvitchinge it, as alſo, that by ſuch vnheedynes he put not the coale of the matche out.</p>
               <p>In the 14. hovv he ſhall ioyne the match againe betvvixt the fingers vvhere he hath had it out at the ſetting of it vp, holding ſtill the peece vp vvards.</p>
               <p>In the 15. hovv he ſhall blovv out the panne ſtanding yet open, and having ſhot of the peece, becanſe (if any ſparck ſhould be remayning therein) the tutch-boxe doe not take fire at the putting in of neevv pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and ſo hurt him ſelf, making (to vvinne tyme) in the meane vvhyle the tutch boxe readie.</p>
               <p>In the 16. hovv he ſhall put the pouder in the panne out of the tutch-boxe, and not out of the charges or flaſke, for not to looſe tyme in dravving or turning of the ſame, holding in the meane tyme the peece vpvvards, for the reaſons a fore ſaid.</p>
               <p>In the 17. hovv he ſhall put to the panne vvith his fore finger like as this figure ſhevveth.</p>
               <p>In the 18. hovv he ſhall caſt or ſhake the pouder or cornes of from the panne, if any might lye vpon it, becauſe the peece ſhall not go of, vvhen he ſhall come to trye the match.</p>
               <p>In the 19. hovv he ſhall blovv of againe the pouder, al thoug he haue ſhaked it of, for more aſſurance.</p>
               <p>In the 20. if he vvill charge againe, hovv he ſhall turne the peece vvith the left hand, vvich to do hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomely, he ſhall convaye it vvith the right hand vnder tovvards the left ſide.</p>
               <p>In the 21. hovv he ſhall lett the peece ſincke by the left ſide, and vvith the right hand take the flaſke or bandelier.</p>
               <p>In the 22. hovv he ſhall open the charge of the flaſke, or els if he doe vveare a bandolier, he ſhall doe like as is ſhevved by the Muſquettiers.</p>
               <p>In the 23. hovv he ſhall put the pouder out of the greater flaſke, holding alvvayes the peece from the ground, if he be able to doe it.</p>
               <p>In the 24. hovv he ſhall vvith a turned hand dravv the ſkovvring ſtick out of the ſtock, and hold the peece from the ground, like as this figure ſhevves.</p>
               <p>In the 25. hovv he deſiring to take the ſkovvring ſtick ſhorter in his hand, ſhall turne the end of the ſame (vvhich is the end that furſt he pulled out (and thruſt it to his bodye, ſlippinge the hand quickly to the neather end, to bringe it the better and the ſteadyer into the peece and if he vvill ſhoote vvith a bullet he ſhall take the bullet vvith the ſame hand (vvherevvith he novv hath the ſkovvring ſtick ſhorter) out of his mouth or from thence vvhere he carrieth his bullets, and vvith like quicknes put it into the mouth of the peece.</p>
               <p>In the 26. hovv he ſhall vvith the ſkovvring-ſtick ramme in the pouder and the bullet together, holding alvvayes the peece from the ground, like as this figure ſhevveth.</p>
               <p>In the 27. hovv he ſhall vvith the in ſyde of his hand turned from hym dravv the ſkovvring ſtick out of the peece, holding alvvayes the peece from the ground.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:5"/>
In the 28. hovv he ſhall (to take ſhorter the ſkovvring-ſtick) thruſt the ſame againe to the bodye, as is taught before.</p>
               <p>In the 29. hovv he ſhall (having the ſkovvring-ſtick vnder and the end) ſurely and vvith ſpeede put the ſame in the ſtock againe.</p>
               <p>In the 30. hovv he (deſirous to take the peece againe in the right hand) ſhall bring the ſame firſt vvith the left hand before him, like as this figure ſhevveth.</p>
               <p>In the 31. hovv he ſhall vvith the right hand take the peece belovve vnder at the great ſkrue, and hold it vpvvards, being readye to laye it againe vpon his ſhoulder.</p>
               <p>In the 32. hovv he ſhall vvith one hand lay the peece againe vpon the ſhoulder, being very readie vvith the other hand, to hold it faſt there vpon.</p>
               <p>In the 33. hovv he having the peece vpon his ſhoulder, going to be ſentinel ſhall hold and carye it againe, like as is ſayd at the firſt figure.</p>
               <p>In the 34. hovv he ſtanding ſentenell and vvill make him readie, ſhall vvith one hand take the peece from the ſhoulder, as is taught before.</p>
               <p>In the 35. hovv he ſtanding ſentenell, and having taken the peece from the ſhoulder, ſhall receiue it in the left hand.</p>
               <p>In the 36. hovv he (ſtanding ſentenell having the peece in the left hand) ſhall hold the right arme or elbovv ſomvvhat from hym vvith his hand at the Seer, and the ſtock againſt the right hippe, like as this fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure teatcheth.</p>
               <p>In the 37. hovv he (ſtanding ſentenell) ſhall hold and gouerne the peece in ballance in the left hand, for to haue the right hand at libertye.</p>
               <p>In the 38. hovv he (ſtanding ſentenell) ſhall vvell and orderly take the match out of the left hand vvith the thumb and ſecond finger.</p>
               <p>In the 36. hovv he (ſtanding ſentenell) ſhall bring the match vvith the thumbe and ſecond finger to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvards the mouth, and blovv it of, holding in the meane time the peece in ballance in the left hand.</p>
               <p>In the 40. hovv he (ſtanding ſentenell) ſhall vvith the thumbe and ſecond finger Cock the match, vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſkruing the ſame in, as is taught before.</p>
               <p>In the 41. hovv he (ſtanding ſentenell) ſhall vvith the thumb and ſecond finger guide and conveniently trye the match.</p>
               <p>In the 42. hovv that he (ſtanding ſentenell that vpon any ſodeine occaſion he maye be readye) ſhall vvith the tvvo foremoſt fingers couer the panne, to prevent the falling of any ſparkes, provided alvvayes that his match be light and Cockt, ready to diſcharge.</p>
               <list>
                  <head>The vvords of Command. By vvhich the Captaynes ſhall command theyr Souldiers orderly, all vvhat they haue to doe vvith the peece. VVhich vvords alſo agree by order vpon every figure.</head>
                  <item>1. Shoulder your Peece and marche.</item>
                  <item>2. Vnſhoulder your Peece.</item>
                  <item>3. And vvith the right hand hold it vp.</item>
                  <item>4. In the left hand take your Peece.</item>
                  <item>5. In the right hand take your matche.</item>
                  <item>6. Hold vvel your match and blovv it of.</item>
                  <item>7. Cock your match.</item>
                  <item>8. Try your match.</item>
                  <item>9. Blovv your match, and open your pann.</item>
                  <item>10. Preſent your Peece.</item>
                  <item>11. Give fire.</item>
                  <item>12. Take dovvne your Peece, and in the left hand hold it vvell.</item>
                  <item>13. Vncock your matche.</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:22852:6"/>
14. And ioyne it againe betvvixt your fingers.</item>
                  <item>15. Blovv out your pan.</item>
                  <item>16. Proyme your pan.</item>
                  <item>17. Shut your pan.</item>
                  <item>18. Shake of your pan.</item>
                  <item>19. Blovv of your pan.</item>
                  <item>20. Turne about your peece.</item>
                  <item>21. And to your left ſide let it ſinke.</item>
                  <item>22. Open your charges.</item>
                  <item>23. Charge your peece.</item>
                  <item>24. Your ſkovvring-ſtick dravv out.</item>
                  <item>25. Your ſkovvring-ſtick take ſhorter.</item>
                  <item>26. Ramme your pouder.</item>
                  <item>27. Your ſkovvring-ſtick dravv out your peece.</item>
                  <item>28. And take it ſhorter.</item>
                  <item>29. Put vp your ſkovvring-ſticke.</item>
                  <item>30. VVith the left hand bring forvvard your Peece.</item>
                  <item>31. And vvith the right hand hold it vp.</item>
                  <item>32. Shoulder your Peece.</item>
                  <item>33. Hold your Peece vvell vpon your ſhoulder, and marche to the place of garde.</item>
                  <item>34. Vnſhoulder your peece.</item>
                  <item>35. And in the left hand let it ſinke.</item>
                  <item>36. Hold your Peece vvell.</item>
                  <item>37. VVith the left hand alone hold your Peece.</item>
                  <item>38. In the right hand take your match.</item>
                  <item>39. Blovv of your match.</item>
                  <item>40. Cock your match.</item>
                  <item>41. Try your match.</item>
                  <item>42. Garde your pan and ſtand readie.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Generall Command.</p>
               <p> Hold vp the mouth of the Peece.</p>
               <p>Here to muſt a Comandour looke, and alvvayes haue his eyes vpon his Souldiers, and vſe them to hold the Peece alvvayes vpvvards, for to prevent all miſchief.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="dut" type="version">
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:6"/>
               <head>CORTE ONDERVVYSINGHE OP DE FIGVERLIICKE AFBEELDINGHE, BELANGHENDE t'rechte ghebruyck des Roers, voor de jonghe ofte onervarene Schutten, vvelcke onder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rechtingh by ſyfer ghetal op elcke figure vervolghens is correſponderende. Ende alſoo noch eenighe ſtilſtaende figuren tot Schiltvvachten hier zijn by gheuoecht, om te vvy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen hoe den Soldaet in tijt van noot (met zijn Roer al ghereet zijnde) ſtaen ſal, ſoo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corderen oock de ſchriften hier van, op elcke figure achtervolghens hun ghetal.</head>
               <head>SCHVTTEN.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Erſtelijck vvort een yeder Schudt in deſe figure ghevveſen, hoe hy vvel ſtaen ofte Marcheren ſal, met een zijn ghevveer als Roer, lont ende rappier houden ende draghen ſal, namentlijcken ſal hy t'Roer met de ſleutel byde ſchouderen comen laten ende t'ſelfde met de lincker handt, niet onder aent eynde vande lade, maer ontrent het duym gadt hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, draghende t'ſelfde altijt achter om hooch, om ſoet Roer onverſiens los gonghe, zijn gheſel gheen ſchade te doen, ende de lont die aen beyden enden branden moet tuſſchen de tvvee kleynſte vingheren vande ſelfde handt voeghen, ende die ſelfde binnen de lade nedervvaerts hanghen laten, om die t'allen tijden langher te connen maecken ende het een deel om t'ander te moghen ghebruycken ende ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vviſſelen, ſal mede altijt behalven fleſſche oft laet maten, een cleyn fleſken met laedt poluer draghen, om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me daer vvt alleen, ende niet vvt de fleſſche, ofte maten het polver in de pan te doen.</p>
               <p>Ten 2. hoe hy int voortagen als hy ſich te ſchieten verdich maecken ſal, zijn Roer vanden hals afnemen moet, te vveten hy en ſal het Roer niet met de lincker handt vande ſchouderen trecken, maer alleen met de rechter handt (ghelijck deſe figure bevvijſt) achter de groote ſchrouve. midts het Roer aldaer gevvichts halven licht is, aengrypen, ende alſoo met een handt daer deur men ſie dat hy des Roers machtich ſy, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemen, latende t'Roer een vveynich inde lincker handt ſincken ſonder t'lichaem daer nae te crommen ofte te buyghen.</p>
               <p>Ten 3. hoe hy t'Roer regieren ende houden ſal eer hy t'ſelfde inde lincker hant nemet, te vveten hy ſal t'Roer met de rechte handt om hooch int ghevvichte houden, ſonder aen het lijf te gheraecken, ende de lincker handt ghereet hebben, om het Roer te ghemoet te comen, ende t'ſelfde daer in te ontfanghen.</p>
               <p>Ten 4. hoe hy t'Roer, als hijt inde lincker hant heeft int ſtae<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ende voort gae<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, niet alleen licht ende vvel draghen, maer oock het ſelfde alſoo int ghevvicht met de ſelfde hant houden ſal, dat het noch te hooch noch te leech en ſy, ende alſoo zijn gheſel indient Roer onverſiens los ginghe gheen ſchade toe en voege, ſettende om lichtheyt ende vaſticheyt vville den ellenboghe tegen de heupe, gelijck deſe figure aenvvijſt.</p>
               <p>Ten 5. hoe hy de lont vvel ende met voordeel vvt de lincker handt met den duym ende den tvveeden vingher nemen ſal, houdende altijt t'Roer in een bequame hoochte, ſoo vvel om de lichtheyt als ooc om zijn gheſel onverſiens gheen ſchade te doen, ende al iſt ſoo datmen (om redenen) generalijcken ſeyt, de lonte te vaetten tuſſchen den duym ende den tvveeden vingher, men nochtans niet en vvil ſegghen, dat een yeghelijck daer ſoo vaſt inghehouden ſy, oft hy en mach de ſelfde vvel tuſſchen den duym ende de tvvee voorſte vinghers vatten, indien hem ſulckx ghemacklijcker viel.</p>
               <p>Ten 6. hoe hy de lonte affblaſe ende tuſſchen den duym ende den tvveeden vingher vvel houden ſal, eer hy de ſelfde op den haen drucket, te vveten hy ſal bequamelijck de lont ontrent den mont brenghen ende de ſelfſte onder de hant affblaſen, ſonder daer nae ſeer te bocken, ghelijck deſe figure aenvvijſt.</p>
               <p>Ten 7. hoe hy de lonte op den haen met den duym ende den tvveeden vingher drucken, ende niet in ſchroeven ſal, om gheen tijt te verlieſen, vvel verſtaende dat hy altijt te voren de vvijdde vanden haen nae de dickte der lonte rechten moet, ten eynde hy des te raſſcher verdich ſy, ende ſchieten mach.</p>
               <p>Ten 8. hoe hy de lonte met voordeel verſoecken, ende met den duym ende den tvveeden vingher, de ſelfde regieren ſal, op dat hy de ſelve terſtont langher corter, als oock hoogher maecken can, ende de ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de alſoo ſtellen, dat hem zijn Roer int ſchieten niet en vveyghere.</p>
               <p>Ten 9. hoe hy t'ſeffens, de lonte raſch ende vvel affblaſen, ende met een gheblaſen hebbende, vvel met
<pb facs="tcp:22852:7"/>
openen armen, ende mette tvvee voorſte vinghers der panne deckſel voorde voncken decken, ende de ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve opdoen ſal, ſonder ſich daer nae te crommen oft te buyghen, brenghende t'Roer met bequaemheyt nae den mont toe, ghelijck deſe figure aenvvijſt.</p>
               <p>Ten 10. hoe hy van boven nedervvaerts, ende niet van onderen opvvaerts aenleggen ſal, op dat hy zijn gheſel die voor hem ſy (ſoo t'Roer onverſiens los ginghe) gheen ſchade en doe, oock om dat den coghel (die altijt inder haeſt niet en kan ghevoedert vverden) niet vvt en rolle.</p>
               <p>Ten 11. hoe hy dat Roer teghen die borſt ſetten, ende aen legghen, t'hooft ſincken, den rechten ellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boge om hooch houden, ende met het lichaem recht ende kloeck ſtaen, ende op dat het Roer op de borſt, ende niet op de ſchouderen aengheleght vverde, t'lichaem daer nae voeghen ſal, daer beneffens hoe hy het lincker been, dat voorſtaen moet, buyghen, ende t'rechter dat achter ſtaen moet, ſtijff houden ſal, ten eynde hy t'Roer des te ghevviſſer regieren, ende los ſchieten (als mede aenlegghen) kan.</p>
               <p>Ten 12. hoe hy gheſchoten hebbende t'Roer vvel vande kaecke aff doen, ende om hooch houden ſal, omme ſoo't Roer ghevveyghert hadde zijn gheſel andervverff gheen ſchade te doen.</p>
               <p>Ten 13. hoe hy de lonte vvel, ende op dat hyſe ſelver niet vvt en leſſche, met de ſelve vinghers daer me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de hy de ſelfde opgheſet heeft, vanden haen afnemen ende niet trecken moet.</p>
               <p>Ten 14. hoe hy de lonte vveder tuſſchen de vinghers voeghen ſal, daer hyſe int op maecken vvt hadde ghenomen, blyvende altijt zijn Roer voor om hooch houdende.</p>
               <p>Ten 15. hoe hy inde pan de vvelcke noch open ſtaende, ende t'Roer los gheſchoten zijnde blaſen ſal, op dat de laedt fleſſche ſoo daer een voncxken op vvaer blyven legghen, niet aen en gae, ende hy ſelve ſchade lyde, maeckende (om tijt te vvinnen) ondertuſſchen het laetfleſken ghereet.</p>
               <p>Ten 16. hoe hy dat laet polver op de panne vvt het laetfleſken, ende niet vvt die maten, ofte groote fleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſche doen ſal, omme doort verrucken van dien, of anderſins, gheen tijt te verlieſen, houdende midlertijt het Roer om redenen voorſz, voor om hooch.</p>
               <p>Ten 17. hoe hy de panne met de voorſten vingher toe doen ſal, ghelijck deſe figure aenvvijſt.</p>
               <p>Ten 18. hoe hy t'polver ſoo daer vvat op der panne deckſel vvaer blijven ligghen affſchudden ſal, op dat vvanneer hy de lonte verſoecken vvilde, het Roer niet onverſiens los en gae.</p>
               <p>Ten 19. hoe hy t'polver, niet teghenſtaende hy t'ſelve afgheſchudt heeft, andermael afblaſen ſal, om alle ſekerheyts vville.</p>
               <p>Ten 20. hoe hy vvillende vvederom laden, het Roer met de lincker hant omdraeyen ſal, omme vvelc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes bequamelijck te doen, ſoo ſal hy t'ſelfde met de rechte handt onder, nae de lincker zijde toe ſtieren.</p>
               <p>Ten 21. hoe hy t'Roer neffens de lincker zyde laten ſincken ſal, ende met de rechterhant nae de fleſſche ofte bandelier vatten.</p>
               <p>Ten 22. hoe hy de mate vande fleſche open doen ſal, oft indien hy een bandelier droech ſoo ſalt ſelfde gheſchieden ghelijck het byde Muſquettiers ghevveſen vvort.</p>
               <p>Ten 23. hoe hy vvt de mate vande groote fleſſche het polver int Roer doen ſal, houdende altijt hetRoer vander acrden, indien hy des ſelfde machtich ſy.</p>
               <p>Ten 24. hoe hy den laedtſtock met een verdraeyde handt vvt de lade ſal trecken, ende t'Roer vander aerden houden, ghelijck deſe figure bevvijſt.</p>
               <p>Ten 25. hoe hy, vvillende den laedtſtock cort vaeten, den ſelfden omghekeert teghens het lijf aen ſtoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſal, ende de hant verdichlijck naert beneden eynde ſchuyuen, om den ſeluen des te gevviſſer int Roer te brengen, ende indien hy met ſcherp vvilde ſchieten, ſal hy het loot met de ſelfde hant, daer hy den laet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtock alſoo cort in ghevat heeft, vvt den mont, oft van daer hy de kogels draecht, verdichlijcken nemen, ende int Roer vallen laten.</p>
               <p>Ten 26. hoe hy met den laedtſtock het poluer ende het loodt ſamen int Roer ſtampen ſal, houdende het Roer altijt vander aerden, ghelijck deſe figure aenvvijſt.</p>
               <p>Ten 27. hoe hy vveder den laedtſtock met een verdraeyde handt vvt het Roer trecken ſal, houdende al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tijt t'Roer vander aerden.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:7"/>
Ten 28. hoe hy om den laetſtock corter te vatten, den ſelfden vveder teghen het lijf aenſtooten ſal, ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lijck te voren gheſeyt is.</p>
               <p>Ten 29. hoe hy hebbende den laedtſtock heel onder aent eynde ghevat, den ſelfden met ghevviſheyt verdichlijck vveder inde lade ſteecken ſal.</p>
               <p>Ten 30. hoe hy vvillende t'Roer vveder inde rechter hant vatten, t'ſelfde eerſt met de lincker hant voor brenghen ſal, ghelijck deſe figure aenvvijſt.</p>
               <p>Ten 31. hoe hy t'Roer inde rechter handt onder aende groote ſchroeve vatten, ende om hooch houden ſal, ghereedt zijnde om t'ſelfde vveder op de ſchouder te legghen.</p>
               <p>Ten 32. hoe hy t'Roer alleen met een handt vveder op de ſchouder legghen ſal, vveſende terſtont ghe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reet met d'ander hant, om t'ſelfde daer op vvel te houden.</p>
               <p>Ten 33. hoe hy t'Roer op ſchouder hebbende, (gaende nae de ſchiltvvacht) t'ſelfde ghelijck byde eerſte figure gheſeyt is, vveder houden ende draghen ſal.</p>
               <p>Ten 34. hoe hy op de ſchiltvvacht ſtaende, ende vvillende hem verdich maken, t'Roer vveder als voren gheſeyt is, met een hant vande ſchouder afnemen ſal.</p>
               <p>Ten 35. hoe hy op de ſchiltvvacht ſtaende, t'Roer vande ſchouder ghenomen hebbende t'ſelfde inde lincker handt ontfanghen ſal.</p>
               <p>Ten 36. hoe hy ſtaende op de ſchiltvvacht, t'Roer inde lincker handt hebbende, den rechten arm van ſich de hant aenden drucker, ende de lade aende rechter heupe houden ſal, ghelijck deſe figure bevvijſt.</p>
               <p>Ten 37. hoe hy ſtaende op de ſchilt vvacht, t'Roer inde lincker handt alleen, int ghevvichte vvel hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den ende regieren ſal, op dat hy de rechter vry hebben mach.</p>
               <p>Ten 38. hoe hy ſtaende op de ſchiltvvacht, de lonte vvel ende met voordeel vvt de lincker hant, met den duym ende den tvveeden vingher nemen ſal.</p>
               <p>Ten 39. hoe hy ſtaende op de ſchiltvvacht, de lonte met den duym ende den tvveeden vingher, naer den mont brenghen ende onder de hant afblaſen ſal, houdende ondertuſſchen het Roer met de lincker hant alleen int ghevvichte.</p>
               <p>Ten 40. hoe hy ſtaende op de ſchiltvvacht, de lonte met den duym ende den tvveeden vingher op den haen drucken ſal, ſonder de ſelfde, ghelijck te voren gheſeyt is, in te ſchroeven.</p>
               <p>Ten 41. hoe hy ſtaende opde ſchiltvvacht, de lonte met den duym ende den tvveeden vingher regieren, ende met voordeel verſoecken ſal.</p>
               <p>Ten 42. hoe hy ſtaende op de ſchiltvvacht, omme in tijt van noot ghereet te zijn, met de lonte opgheſet ſtaen, ende de panne voor de voncken (mette tvvee voorſte vingheren) bedecken ſal.</p>
               <list>
                  <head>De vvoorden van commandement. VVaer mede de Capiteynen hun Soldaten vervolghehs ghebieden al t'ghene ſy met het Roer hebben te doen, vvelcke vvoorden oock vervolghens op elcke figure zijn accorderende.</head>
                  <item>1. Op u ſchouder u Roer vvel hout ende Marcheert.</item>
                  <item>2. Van u ſchouder u Roer neemt.</item>
                  <item>3. Ende met de rechter hant om hooch hout.</item>
                  <item>4. Inde lincker handt u Roer neemt.</item>
                  <item>5. V lonte inde rechterhant neemt.</item>
                  <item>6. V lont afblaeſt, ende vvel hout.</item>
                  <item>7. V lont opdruckt.</item>
                  <item>8. V lont verſoeckt.</item>
                  <item>9. V lont afblaeſt ende u pan opent.</item>
                  <item>10. V Roer aenleght.</item>
                  <item>11. Schiet.</item>
                  <item>12. V Roer affneemt ende mette lincker hant vvel hout.</item>
                  <item>13. V lont afneemt.</item>
                  <item>14. Ende vveder tuſſchen de vinghers voecht.</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:22852:8"/>
15. V pan affblaeſt.</item>
                  <item>16. Op u pan polver doet.</item>
                  <item>17. V pan toedoet.</item>
                  <item>18. V pan affſchut.</item>
                  <item>19. V pan affblaeſt.</item>
                  <item>20. V Roer omdraeyt.</item>
                  <item>21. Ende neffens u lincker zijde ſincken laet.</item>
                  <item>22. V mate open doet.</item>
                  <item>23. V Roer ladet.</item>
                  <item>24. V laedtſtock vvttrect.</item>
                  <item>25. V laedtſtock cort vat.</item>
                  <item>26. V polver neer ſtampt.</item>
                  <item>27. V laedt ſtock vvt u Roer trect.</item>
                  <item>28. Ende cort vat.</item>
                  <item>29. V laedt ſtock op ſteect.</item>
                  <item>30. V Roer met de lincker hant voor brenght.</item>
                  <item>31. Ende mette rechter hant om hooch hout.</item>
                  <item>32. Op u ſchouder u Roer leght.</item>
                  <item>33. Op u ſchouder u Roer vvel hout, ende Marcheert nae de ſchiltvvacht.</item>
                  <item>34. Van u ſchouder u Roer neemt.</item>
                  <item>35. Ende inde lincker hant ſincken laet.</item>
                  <item>36. V Roer vvel hout.</item>
                  <item>37. V Roer inde lincker hant alleen hout.</item>
                  <item>38. V lont inde rechter hant vat.</item>
                  <item>39. V lont affblaeſt.</item>
                  <item>40. V lont opdruct.</item>
                  <item>41. V lont verſoect.</item>
                  <item>42. V pan deckt, ende ghereet ſtaet.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Generael commandement.</p>
               <p> V loop om hooch hout.</p>
               <p>Hier op moet beſonder een bevel hebber acht nemen, dat hy altijt het oogh op zijn Soldaten hebbe ende hunluyden gevvenne t'Roer altijt met den loop om hooch te houden, om alle ongelucken te verhoeden.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="illustrations">
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:8"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <head>IDGheÿn. in, 1</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:9"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:9"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>2</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:10"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:10"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>3</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:11"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:11"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>4</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:12"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:12"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>5</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:13"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:13"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>6</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:14"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:14"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>7</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:15"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:15"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>8</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:16"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:16"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>9</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:17"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:17"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>10</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:18"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:18"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>11</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:19"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:19"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>12</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:20"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:20"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>13</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:21"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:21"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>14</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:22"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:22"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>15</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:23"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:23"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>16</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:24"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:24"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>17</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:25"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:25"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>18</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:26"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:26"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>19</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:27"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:27"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>20</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:28"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:28"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>21</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:29"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:29"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>22</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:30"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:30"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>23</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:31"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:31"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>24</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:32"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:32"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>25</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:33"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:33"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>26</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:34"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:34"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>27</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:35"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:35"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>28</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:36"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:36"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>29</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:37"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:37"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>30</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:38"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:38"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>31</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:39"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:39"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>32</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:40"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:40"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>33</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:41"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:41"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>34</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:42"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:42"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>35</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:43"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:43"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>36</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:44"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:44"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>37</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:45"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:45"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>38</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:46"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:46"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>39</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:47"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:47"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>40</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:48"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:48"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>41</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:49"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:49"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>42</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <div xml:lang="eng" type="version">
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:50"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:50"/>
               <head>SHORTE INSTRVC<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION FOR THE FIGVRES; SO MVCH AS CONCERNETH THE RIGHT VSE OF MVS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kett for the yonge or inexpert Souldier, vvhich inſtruction doth orderly agree vvith the Cypher letters of eche figure. And becauſe there be ſome figures of ſtilſtandinghe poſtures here after annexed, as found fitt for ſentinels to vſe, to ſhevv hovv a ſouldier in tyme of neede ſhall ſtand readie vvith his Muſket in the Muſket reſt, therefore are the ſayd inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions follovving appropriated to euery figure according to theyr number.</head>
               <head type="sub">MVSKETTIER.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt of all is ſhevved to every Muſkettier, hovv he ſhall handſomely carye his Muſket and his Muſket reſt, That is to ſaye: that he having the reſt in his right hand, ſhall at euery pace vvhen he goeth, ſet it forevvard in the earth, having a fore hand made a little ſtring at it, for to trayle the ſame if need be, letting the Muſket come vvith the ſkrue (vvhich is faſt by the Seer) cloſe to the ſhoulder, the hand about the hollovve or thumplace, and the matche burning or kindled at bothe endes, betvveene the tvvoo ſmaleſt fingers, of the ſame hand, lettingh the ſame hange dovvne at the inſide of the ſtock, becauſe he may put it vp at all occaſions (if need be) and to vſe the one and the other ende by changing, ſhal alſo alvvayes beſides flaſke or charges, haue a tutch boxe vvith tutch pouder, to put onely out of the ſame the pouder in the panne.</p>
               <p>In the 2. figure is ſhevved, hovv he ſhall in an other maner carye his Muſket reſt, vvhen he vvill make him readie to ſhoote, that is to ſaye, he ſhall carye the reſt cloſe to the Muſkett in the left hand, letting the reſt (ſo farre als the Iron is) come aboue the hand, like as this figure ſhevveth.</p>
               <p>In the 3, hovv he ſhall, vvhen he vvill take the Muſket from his neck let the Muſket reſt ſinke a little through the left hand vvithout help of the right hand, and together vvith the right hand alone, eaſelye take the Muſket from his ſhoulder, and take hold beyond the great ſkrue, becauſe the Muſket is there (in regard of his vveight) lighter, letting the ſame ſinke a little in the left hand, vvithout bending the bodye to it.</p>
               <p>In the 4. hovv he ſhall hold vp the Muſket vvith the right hand onely for to receiue the ſame vvith the reſt in the left hand, that is: he ſhall not let the Muſket fall in the other hand, but ſhall meet it vvith the left hand, and ioyne the ſame betvvixt the thumbe and the reſt handſomelye.</p>
               <p>In the 5. hovv he ſhall hold the Muſket vvith the reſt in the left hand onely, and that the Muſket be neither to highe nor to lovve, but in ballance, and haue his right hand free, ſetting the elbovve for the more ſtrenght, againſt his hyppe, vvithout trayling the Muſket reſt, onles the ſouldier vveare to vveake or to vvearye.</p>
               <p>In the 6. hovv he ſhall vvell and readily take the matche out of the left hand vvith the thumbe and the ſecond finger holding euer the Muſket in a due height.</p>
               <p>In the 7. (having taken the matche betvvixt the thumbe and ſecond finger) hovv he ſhall bring the match to the mouth and blovv it of vvithout bovvinge hym to much tovvardes it.</p>
               <p>In the 8. hovv vvith the thumbe and ſecond finger he ſhall orderly cocke the match, and not ſkrue it in hauing before directed the vvideneffe of the cocke to the thickneſſe of the matche.</p>
               <p>In the 9. hovv he ſhall handſomely trye and gouerne the matche vvith the thumbe and ſecond finger to the ende he maye preſently ſet it higher, lovver, longer or ſhorter.</p>
               <p>In the 10. hovv he ſhall blovv of the match and together vvith the tvvo fore fingers couer the pan lidde (for feare of ſparkes falling therin) and alſo open the ſame handſomely.</p>
               <p>In the 11. hovv having layde the Muſket in the reſt (keeping alvvayes the mouth of it at a reaſonable height) ſetting the left legge before and the Muſket reſt ſo me vvhat forvvard, he ſhall be then readie to preſent.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:51"/>
In the 12. hovv he ſhall preſent vvell and hold the Muſket and the reſt in the left hand, bearing the right arme or elbovv ſomvvhat vp and turning a little the bodye to the left ſide, the left knee bovved and the right legge ſtraight, and this not onely for faſhions ſake, but alſo that the Muſkett may be helde and ſhott of the ſurer. Beſides muſt be regarded that vvhen he vvill preſent, he ſet the Muſket hard (not againſt the ſhoulder) but againſt the breſt: for it is ſo more gracefull beſides he ſhall not laye his cheeke to the ſtocke before he haue ſet the Muſket to his breſt, becauſe it hath other vvayes no grace, much leſſe can he ſhoote ſurely but to the contrarie for the moſt part ſlubbers it ouer in haſte.</p>
               <p>In the 13. hovv he having diſcharged ſhall truſt the Muſket a little forvvard, take vp the reſt and hold the ſame vvith the Muſket in the ſame hand, and not trayle it, onles he vvere to vvearie holding alvvayes the Muſket vp, for feare of hurting any man, if the Muſket ſhould chaunce not to haue gone of.</p>
               <p>In the 14. hovv he ſhall oderley take the matche out of the cock vvith the ſame fingers he put it in, not pluckinge or ſnatchinge it out for feare of deadinge the coale.</p>
               <p>In the 15. hovv he ſhall ioyne againe the match betvvixt the fingers vvhere he hath taken it out, and euer hold the Muſket in a meet height.</p>
               <p>In the 16. hovv he ſhall blovv of the ſparkes, if any be remayned in the pann, to the ende the tutch-boxe do not take fire, vvhen he vvill put pouder in it, vvhere by he might hurt him ſelf, having in the meane ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me the tutch-boxe in the right hand, for to looſe no tyme.</p>
               <p>In the 17. hovv he ſhall put pouder in the pann out of the tutch box, and not out of the charges, becauſe the charges are dravvne to and fro in charginge, and that is a great hinderance to the quicknes required in ſhooting.</p>
               <p>In the 18. hovv he ſhall ſhutt the panne vvith the fore finger like, as this figure ſhevveth.</p>
               <p>In the 19. hovv he ſhall caſt the tutch pouder from the pann lidde, to the ende the Muſket doe not go of vnadviſedlye vvhen he comes to trye the match.</p>
               <p>In the 20. hovv he ſhall blovv the pouder of the pann lidde if any vvere remained there on, for more aſſurance.</p>
               <p>In the 21. hovv (to charge againe) he ſhall turne the Muſket vvith the reſt guydinge, or as it vvere, ſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe the ſame at the lovver part or end vvith the right hand tovvards the left ſide.</p>
               <p>In the 22. hovv he having turned the Muſket ſhall let the ſame ſinke to the left ſide and trayle the reſt, and to doe it more convenientlye the right hand muſt preſently ſuccour the left.</p>
               <p>In the 23. hovv he ſhall truſt open the charges vvith the tumbe, trayle the reſt and hold the Muſket from the ground, if he be able.</p>
               <p>In the 24. hovv he ſhall charge the Muſket out of the charges, letting the Muſket reſt yet trayle, but no vvaye ſufferinge the Muſket to come to the ground, if he be not to vvearie.</p>
               <p>In the 25. hovv he ſhall vvith a turned hand dravv the ſkovvringſtick out of the ſtock, traylinge the reſt but not the Muſket.</p>
               <p>In the 26. (deſirous to take ſhorter the ſkovvring-ſtick) hovv he ſhall thruſt the ſame (turned) againſt the bodye letting the hand ſlippe haſtely to the neather ende for to bring it the ſurer in the Muſket and if he vvill ſhoote vvith a bullet, he ſhall vvith the ſame hand that tooke ſhorter the ſkovvring-ſtick, take ſpeedely the bullet out of his mouthe or place vvhere he vſually carrieth them, and ſo let it fall or roule into the Muſket.</p>
               <p>In the 27. hovv he ſhall vvith the ſkovvring-ſtick ramme the pouder and bullet together in the Muſket trayling ſtill the reſt but not the Muſket, if he be ſtrong ynough.</p>
               <p>In the 28. hovv he ſhall vvith a turned hand dravv the ſkovvring ſtick out of the Muſket againe, trayling the reſt but the Muſket from the ground, if he be able.</p>
               <p>In the 29. hovv (to take the ſkovvring-ſtick ſhorter) he ſhall ſet the ſame againe to the bodye, as is ſayd before.</p>
               <p>In the 30. hovv (having the ſkovvring-ſtick vnder at the ende) he ſhall put the ſame ſurely and ſpeedely againe in the ſtock.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:51"/>
In the 31. hovv (deſiring to take the Muſket againe in the right hand) he ſhall firſt bring it forvvard vvith the left hand, like as this figure ſhevveth.</p>
               <p>In the 32. hovv he ſhall take the Muſket againe vvith the right hand at the great ſkrue and hold it vp, letting the Muſkett reſt (vvhich is yet trayling) come forvvard the lenght off the ſtring, to make it come readely in the left hand.</p>
               <p>In the 33. hovv he ſhall lightlye vvith one hand laye the Muſket vpon the ſhoulder, and yet in the meane tyme hold the reſt.</p>
               <p>In the 34. hovv he, having layd the Muſket vpon the ſhoulder, ſhall againe carrye and hold the ſame, as is alreadie ſayd.</p>
               <p>In the 35. hovv he (deſiringe to make him readye, ſtanding ſentinell) ſhall vvith one hand againe (as is ſayd) take the Muſket from the ſhoulder.</p>
               <p>In the 36. hovv, vvhen he is in his place of ſentinell and vvill faſhion him felfe to his poſture or garde, he ſhall laye the Muſket in the reſt, like as this figure teatcheth.</p>
               <p>In the 37. hovv (being novv ſentinell, and the Muſket laye in the reſt) he ſhall bear his right arme or elbovv from hym, holding his hand at the Seer, and keeping the ſtock of the peece cloſe to his right hippe: like as this figure ſhevveth.</p>
               <p>In the 38. hovv he, ſtanding ſentenell, ſhall hold before hym the Muſket in the reſt, ſo that he (having the Muſket in ballance) maye governe the ſame vvith the left hand onely, and haue free the right hand: as this figure ſhevveth.</p>
               <p>In the 39. hovv he (ſtanding ſentinell) ſhall take the match vvell and convenientlye vvith the thumbe and fore finger out of the left hand.</p>
               <p>In the 40. hovv he (ſtandinge ſentinell) ſhall vvith the thumbe and fore finger bring the match to his mouth and blovv it of vnder the hand, holdinge in the meane tyme the Muſket in due ballance vpon the Reſt, and that vvith the lefte hand onelye.</p>
               <p>In the 41. hovv he (ſtanding ſentinell) vvith the tumbe and fore finger ſhall cocke the matche vvithout ſkruyng the ſame in, as is ſaid before.</p>
               <p>In the 42. hovv he (ſtandinge ſentinell) vvith the thumbe and fore finger ſhall guyde and trye the match handſomelye, holding (as is ſayd) the Muſket ſtill in ballance.</p>
               <p>In the 43. hovv he (ſtanding ſentinell to be readye in tyme of need) ſhall ſtand vvith his matche cockte and the panne garded (for feare of ſparkes) vvith the tvvo fore fingers.</p>
               <list>
                  <head>The vvords of Command. VVhere by the Capitaynes ſhall orderly comand theyr Souldiers all vvhat they have to do vvith theyr Muſket and Muſket reſt, vvhich vvords are alſo agreeing by ordre vvith every figure.</head>
                  <item>1. Marche vvith the Muſket reſt in your hand.</item>
                  <item>2. Marche, and vvith the Muſket carye the reſt.</item>
                  <item>3. Sinke your reſt and vnſhoulder your Muſket.</item>
                  <item>4. Hold vp your Muſket vvith the right hand and let it ſinke in the left.</item>
                  <item>5. In the left hand hold your Muſket and carye your reſt vvith it.</item>
                  <item>6. Take your match in the right hand.</item>
                  <item>7. Blovv of your match and hold it vvell.</item>
                  <item>8. Cock your match.</item>
                  <item>9. Trye your match.</item>
                  <item>10. Blovv of your match and open your pann.</item>
                  <item>11. Hold vp your Muſket and preſent.</item>
                  <item>12. Give fire.</item>
                  <item>13. Take dovvne your Muſket and carye it vvith your reſt.</item>
                  <item>14. Vncock your match.</item>
                  <item>15. And put it againe betvvixt your fingers.</item>
                  <item>16. Blovv your pan.</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:22852:52"/>
17. Proyme your pan.</item>
                  <item>18. Shut your pan.</item>
                  <item>19. Caſt of your pan.</item>
                  <item>20. Blovv your pan.</item>
                  <item>21. Caſt about your Muſket.</item>
                  <item>22. Trayle your reſt.</item>
                  <item>23. Open your charges.</item>
                  <item>24. Charge your Muſket.</item>
                  <item>25. Dravv out your ſkovvring-ſtick.</item>
                  <item>26. Shorten your ſkovvring-ſticke.</item>
                  <item>27. Ramme in your pouder.</item>
                  <item>28. Dravv your ſkovvringe-ſticke out of your Muſket.</item>
                  <item>29. Shorten your ſkovvringe-ſticke.</item>
                  <item>30. Put vp your ſkovvringe-ſticke.</item>
                  <item>31. Bring your Muſket forvvard vvith the left hand.</item>
                  <item>32. And hold it vp vvith the right hand and recouer your reſt.</item>
                  <item>33. Shoulder your Muſket.</item>
                  <item>34. March and carye your reſt vvith your Muſket.</item>
                  <item>35. Vnſhoulder your Muſket.</item>
                  <item>36. Lay your Muſket in the reſt.</item>
                  <item>37. Hold your Muſket on the reſt.</item>
                  <item>38. Hold your Muſket in the reſt, and vvith the left hand onely in ballance.</item>
                  <item>39. Take your match in the right hand.</item>
                  <item>40. Blovv of your match.</item>
                  <item>41. Cock your match.</item>
                  <item>42. Try your match.</item>
                  <item>43. Garde your pann, and be readie.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Generall Command.</p>
               <p> Hold vp your Muſket.</p>
               <p>And in regard it is a matter of no ſmall conſequence, a comandour ſhall alvvayes haue a ſpeciall care and eye to his Souldiers to accuſtome them to hold euer the Muſket vvith the mouth vp, the better to preuent all miſchieff.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="dut" type="version">
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:52"/>
               <head>CORTE ONDERRECHTINGHE OP DE FIGVERLIICKE AFBEELDINGHE, SOO VEEL AEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaet het recht ghebruyck vant Muſquet, voor de jonghe ofte onervaren Soldaten, vvelc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke onderrechting by ſijfer ghetal op elcke figure vervolghens is correſponderende. Ende alſoo noch eenighe ſtilſtaende figueren tot ſchiltvvachten hier achter aen gevoecht zijn, om te vvijſen hoe den Soldaet in tijt van noot met zijn Muſquet inde furquet liggende, al ghereet ende verdich ſtaen ſal, ſoo accorderen oock de ſchriften van deſe, op elcke fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure vervolghens hun ghetal.</head>
               <head type="sub">MVSQVETTIER.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>En Eerſten vvort een yder Muſquettier ghevveſen hoe hy int voortgaen zijn Muſquet ende furquet, bequamelijcken draghen ſal, als te vveten dat hy, hebbende de fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet inde rechter handt, de ſelfde int voortgaen, t'elcke mael op der aerden voort ſetten ſal, hebbende oock daer aen te voeren een koordeken vaſt ghemaeckt, om de ſelfde alſt van noode ſy te moghen ſleypen, latende het Muſquet met de ſleutel dicht by de ſchouder comen, de hant ontrent het duym gat, ende de lonte die aen beyde eynden branden moet tuſſchen de tvvee cleynſte vinghers vande ſelfde hant voeghen, ende de ſelfde binnen de lade nedervvaerts hanghen laten, om die t'allen tijden langher te connen maecken, ende het een deel om t'ander te moghen gebruycken ende vervviſſelen, ſal mede altijt behalven fleſſche oft laedt maten een cleyn fleſken met laedt polver dragen, om daer vvt alleen het polver inde pan te doen.</p>
               <p>Ten 2. hoe hy op een ander maniere zijn furquet draghen ſal, als hy hem tot ſchieten ſal vvillen verdich maecken, te vveten hy ſal het furquet neffens de Muſquet inde lincker hant draghen, latende de furquet ſoo langhe het yſer is boven de hant ſchieten, ghelijck deſe figure bevvijſt.</p>
               <p>Ten 3. hoe hy de furquet vvanneer hy de Muſquet vanden hals nemen vvil, deur de linckerhant ſonder hulpe der rechter een vveynich ſal laten ſincken, ende met <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Muſquet lichteliick vande ſchouder met de rechter hant alleen nemen, ende achter de groote ſchroeve aengrijpen, om dieſvvil het Muſquet aldaer ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvichts halven lichſt is, latende t'ſelfde een vveynich inde lincker handt ſincken, ſonder t'lichaem daer nae te crommen oft te buyghen.</p>
               <p>Ten 4. hoe hy de Muſquet met de rechter hant alleen om hooch houden ſal, om t'ſelfde neffens de fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet inde lincker hant te ontfanghen, als te vveten hy en ſal het Muſquet in d'ander hant niet laten vallen, maer ſal met de lincker hant de Muſquet te ghemoet comen, ende t'ſelfde daer tuſſchen de furquet ende den duym bequamelijcken in voeghen.</p>
               <p>Ten 5. hoe hy de Muſquet neffens de furquet inde lincker hant alleen, mits dat de Muſquet noch te hooch noch te leech en ſy int ghevvichte houden, ende de rechter hant vry hebben ſal, ſettende den ellenboghe om meerder vaſticheyts vville teghens de heupe, ſonder de furquet te ſlepen, ten vvaer den Soldaet te ſvvack ofte moede vvaer.</p>
               <p>Ten 6. hoe hy de lonte vvel, ende met voordeel vvt de lincker hant, met den duym ende den tvveeden vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger nemen ſal, houdende altijt het Muſquet in een bequame hoochte.</p>
               <p>Ten 7. hoe hy de lonte, de vvelcke hy tuſſchen den duym ende den tvveeden vinger ghevat heeft, naer den mont brengen ende afblaſen ſal, ſonder daer naer ſeer te boucken.</p>
               <p>Ten 8. hoe hy de lonte metten duym ende den tvveeden vingher vvel op drucken, ende niet inſchrou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſal, ten vvelcken eynde hy die vvijte vanden haen nae de dickte der lonte gherecht moet houden.</p>
               <p>Ten 9. hoe hy de lonte met voordeel verſoecken ende metten duym ende den tvveeden vingher regieren ſal, op dat hy de ſelve terſtont langer, corter, als oock hooger ende legher maecken can.</p>
               <p>Ten 10. hoe hy de lonte affblaſen ſal, ende met eene<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, met de tvvee vorſte vingers der panne deckſel (op dat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter geen voncken vande lont op en vallen) decken, ende de ſelve bequamelijck op doen ſal.</p>
               <p>Ten 11. hoe hy de Muſquet inde furquet leggende, de ſelfde voor om hooch houde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, het lincker been voor
<pb facs="tcp:22852:53"/>
ſtellen, met een de furquet voorvvaerts vvt ſetten, om als dan aen te legghen.</p>
               <p>Ten 12. hoe hy vvel aenlegghen, en die Muſquet ende furquet met de lincker hant houden ſal, den rechter arm om hooch, en t'lijff ghed. aeyt, de lincker knie buyghen, ende de rechter ſtijf houden, op dattet niet alleen te beter ſtaen, maer oock de Muſquet des te ghevviſſer gehouden, ende geſchoten moech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te vverden, daer beneffens moet achtinghe ghenomen vvorden vvanneer hy aenlegghen vvil, dat hy de Muſquet vvelſtaens halven, hert aenſette, ende dat niet teghen de ſchouder maer teghen de borſt, ooc niet eer de kaecke teghen de lade legghen, hy en hebbe dan de Muſquet te voren teghen de borſt gheſet, alſoot anders gheen gratie en heeft, veel vveynigher men ghevviſſelijck ſchieten can, maer men ſich meeren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deels verhaeſtet.</p>
               <p>Ten 13. hoe hy gheſchoten hebbende, de Muſquet een vveynich voorſich ſtooten ſal, de furquet vveder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>om opnemen ende deſelve inde hant vaſt, neffens de Muſquet houden, ende niet ſlepen ſal, ten vvare hy te ſvvack vvare, houdende altijt de Muſquet omhooch om <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>emant (ſoo de Muſquet ghevveyghert hadde) te quetſen.</p>
               <p>Ten 14. hoe hy de lonte vvel, ende op dat hijſe ſelver niet vvt en leſſche, met de vinghers daer mede hy de ſelfde op gheſet heeft, vanden haen nemen ende niet trecken moet.</p>
               <p>Ten 15. hoe hy de lonte vveder tuſſchen de vingheren, daer hijſe te voren vvt ghenomen heeft, voeghen ſal, houdende altijt t'Muſquet in bequame hoochte.</p>
               <p>Ten 16. hoe hy de voncken, ſoo daer op de panne iet mochte ligghen, affblaſen ſal, op dat het laedtfleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken niet aen en gae, als hy t'polver daer op ſchudden vvil, vvaer door hy ſich ſelven mochte quetſen, heb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bende onder tuſſchen het laedtfleſken (om tijt te vvinnen) inde rechter hant ghereet ghevat.</p>
               <p>Ten 17. hoe hy dat polver vvt het laedtfleſken (ende niet vvt de maten) op de panne doen ſal, vvant de vvijle de maten ladens halven verruckt vvorden, ſoo hindert ſulckx int verdich ſchieten ſeer.</p>
               <p>Ten 18. hoe hy de panne met de voorſte vingher toe doen ſal, ghelijck deſe figure bevvijſt.</p>
               <p>Ten 19. hoe hy het laedt polver vander panne deckſel af ſchudden ſal, ten eynde de Muſquet, vvanneer hy de lonte verſoecken vvil, niet onverſiens los en gae.</p>
               <p>Ten 20. hoe hy ten overvlo<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> dat laedt polver vander panne <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> lig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghen, aff blaſen ſal, om alle ſeeckerheyts vville.</p>
               <p>Ten 21. hoe hy de Muſquet (omme vveder te laden) met de furquet omdraeyen ſal, ſtierende de ſelfde beneden met de rechter hant, naer de lincker zijde toe.</p>
               <p>Ten 22. hoe hy de Muſquet omgedraeyt hebbende, de ſelfde neffens de lincker zijde late<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſincke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ende de furquet ſlepen ſal, en om ſulckx bequamelijck te connen doen, moet de rechte hant de lincker terſtont te hulpe comen.</p>
               <p>Ten 23. hoe hy de mate met den duym open douvven ſal, de furquet laten ſlepen, ende de Muſquet van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der aerden houden, indien hy de ſelfde machtich ſy.</p>
               <p>Ten 24, hoe hy, vvt de mate de Muſquet laden ſal, latende de furquet noch al ſlepen, ſonder de Muſquet teghen d aerde te ſlepen, ten vvare hy te ſvvack vvaer.</p>
               <p>Ten 25. hoe hy den laedtſtock met een verdraeyde hant, vvt de lade trecken ſal, ende de furquet als noch laten ſlepen, maer niet de Muſquet.</p>
               <p>Ten 26, hoe hy vvillende den laedtſtock corter vatten, den ſelfden omgekeert teghen t'lijff aen ſtooten ſal, ſchuyvende de hant terſtont naert beneden eynde toe, om des te ghevviſſer den ſelfden inde Muſquet te connen ſteecken, ende indien hy met ſcherp vvilde ſchieten, ſal hy het loot met de ſelfde hant, daer hy den laedt ſtoc alſoo cort in ghevaet heeft, vvt den mont, oft van daer hy de koghels draecht, verdichlijcken nemen, ende int Muſquet rollen laten.</p>
               <p>Ten 27. hoe hy met de laedtſtock, het polver ende het loot ſamen int Muſquet ſtampen ſal, latende de furquet noch al ſlepen, maer niet de Muſquet, indien hy de ſelſde machtich ſy.</p>
               <p>Ten 28. hoe hy vveder de laedt ſtoc met een verdraeyde hant vvt het Muſquet treckenſal, de furquet ſle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, ende de Muſquet vander aerden houden indien hy des machtich ſy.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:53"/>
Ten 29. hoe hy om den laedtſtock corter te vatten, den ſelfden ander mael, teghen het lijfaen ſtooten ſal, als voorſeyt is.</p>
               <p>Ten 30. hoe hy hebbende den laedtſtock heel onder aent eynde ghevat, den ſelfden met ghevviſheyt ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dichlijck vveder inde lade ſteecken ſal.</p>
               <p>Ten 31. hoe hy vvillende d'Muſquet vveder inde hant vatten, t'ſelfde eerſt met de lincker hant voor-brenghen ſal, ghelijck deſe figure bevvijſt.</p>
               <p>Ten 32. hoe hy de Muſquet mette rechterhant by de groote ſchrouve vvederom vatten ende om hooch houden ſal, latende de furquet (die noch ſleypt) ſoo lanck het coordeken is voor vvt ſchieten, om met voor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deel de ſelfde te doen inde lincker hant comen.</p>
               <p>Ten 33. hoe hy de Muſquet vvel lichtlijcken ende met een hant op de ſchouder legghen, ende onder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuſſchen de furquet houden ſal.</p>
               <p>Ten 34. hoe hy hebbende de Muſquet op de ſchouder gheleght, de ſelfde (vveder als voren) houden ende draghen ſal.</p>
               <p>Ten 35. hoe hy vvillende hem (op de ſchilt vvacht ſtaende) verdich maecken, zijn Muſquet vveder als voren gheſeyt is, met een hant vande ſchouder aff nemen ſal.</p>
               <p>Ten 36. hoe hy vvillende hem ſtellen op de ſchilt vvacht, het Muſquet inde furquet leggen ſal, ghelijck deſe figure bevvijſt.</p>
               <p>Ten 37. hoe hy ſtaende op de ſchilt vvacht, de Muſquet inde furquet ligghende, den rechten arm van ſich, de hant aenden drucker, ende de lade aende rechter heupe houden ſal, ghelijck deſe figure bevvijſt.</p>
               <p>Ten 38. hoe hy ſtaende op de ſchiltvvacht, de furquet met de Muſquet daer inne leggende, voorſich hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den ſal, ſulckx dat hy de Muſquet int ghevvichte, ende met de lincker hant alleen regieren, ende de rechter vry hebben mach: ghelijck de figure bevvijſt.</p>
               <p>Ten 39. hoe hy ſtaende op de ſchiltvvacht, de lonte vvel ende met voordeel (vvt de lincker hant) met den duym ende den tvveeden vingher nemen ſal.</p>
               <p>Ten 40. hoe hy ſtaende op de ſchiltvvacht, de lonte, met den duym ende den tvveeden vingher, naer den mont brenghen ende onder de hant afblaſen ſal. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> he<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Muſquet inde furquet (met de lincker hant alleen) int ghevvichte legghen.</p>
               <p>Ten 41. hoe hy ſtaende op de ſchiltvvacht de lonte met den duym ende den tvveeden vingher op den haen drucken ſal, ſonder de ſelfde (ghelijck te voren gheſeyt is) in te ſchroeven.</p>
               <p>Ten 42. hoe hy ſtaende op de ſchiltvvacht, de lonte met den duym ende den tvveeden vingher regeren, ende met voordeel verſoecken ſal, houdende als gheſeyt is het Muſquet int ghevvichte.</p>
               <p>Ten 43. hoe hy ſtaende op de ſchiltvvacht, omme in tijt van noot ghereet te zijn, met de lonte opgheſet ſtaen, ende de panne voor de voncken met de tvvee voorſte vingheren bedecken ſal.</p>
               <list>
                  <head>Devvoorden van commandement. VVaer door de Capiteynen hun Soldaten vervolghens ghebieden al t'ghene ſy met hun Muſquet ende furquet hebben te doen, vvelcke vvoorden oock vervolghens op elcke figure zijn accorderende.</head>
                  <item>1. Marcheert met de furquet inde hant.</item>
                  <item>2. Marcheert ende draecht de furquet neffens de Muſquet.</item>
                  <item>3. V furquet ſincken laet, en van u ſchouder u Muſquet neemt.</item>
                  <item>4. Mette rechter hant u Muſquet om hooch hout, ende inde lincker hant ſincken laet.</item>
                  <item>5. Inde lincker ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t u Muſquet neemt, ende u furquet neffens de Muſquet draecht.</item>
                  <item>6. V lonte inde rechterhant neemt.</item>
                  <item>7. V lont afblaeſt, ende vvel hout.</item>
                  <item>8. V lont opdruckt.</item>
                  <item>9. V lont verſoeckt.</item>
                  <item>10. V lont afblaeſt, en u pan opent.</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:22852:54"/>
11. V Muſquet om hooch hout ende aenlegt.</item>
                  <item>12. Schiet.</item>
                  <item>13. V Muſquet afneemt ende neffens u furquet draecht.</item>
                  <item>14. V lont afneemt.</item>
                  <item>15. Ende voechtſe vveder tuſſchen de vinghers.</item>
                  <item>16. V pan affblaeſt.</item>
                  <item>17. Op u pan polver doet.</item>
                  <item>18. V pan toedoet.</item>
                  <item>19. V pan affſchut.</item>
                  <item>20. V pan affblaeſt.</item>
                  <item>21. V Muſquet omdraeyt.</item>
                  <item>22. Ende u furquet ſleypt.</item>
                  <item>23. V mate op doet.</item>
                  <item>24. V Muſquet ladet.</item>
                  <item>25. V laedtſtock vvttrect.</item>
                  <item>26. V laedtſtock cort vat.</item>
                  <item>27. V polver neer ſtampt.</item>
                  <item>28. V laedtſtock <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> u Muſquet <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rect.</item>
                  <item>29. V laedtſtock cort vat.</item>
                  <item>30. V laedtſtock op ſteect.</item>
                  <item>31. V Muſquet met de lincker hant voor brenght.</item>
                  <item>32. Ende met de rechter hant om hooch hout, ende u furquet hervat.</item>
                  <item>33. Op u ſchouder u Muſquet leght.</item>
                  <item>34. Marcheert ende draecht de furquet neffens de Muſquet.</item>
                  <item>35. Van u ſchouder u Muſquet neemt.</item>
                  <item>36. V Muſquet inde furquet leght.</item>
                  <item>37. Op u furquet u Muſquet hout.</item>
                  <item>38. V Muſquet inde furquet, met de lincker hant alleen int ghevvicht houdt.</item>
                  <item>39. V lont inde rechter hant vat.</item>
                  <item>40. V lont affblaeſt.</item>
                  <item>41. V lont opdruct.</item>
                  <item>42. V lont verſoect.</item>
                  <item>43. V pan deckt, ende ghereet ſtaet.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Generael commandement.</p>
               <p> V loop om hooch hout.</p>
               <p>Ende alſoo hier in ſeer veel is gheleghen, ſoo moet beſonder een bevelhebber hier op groote achtinghe nemen, ende altijt zijn oogh op zijn Soldaten houden, en deſelve gevvennen t'Muſquet altijt met den loop om hooch te houden, om te verhoeden alle ongelucken.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="illustrations">
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:54"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>IDGheÿn. in, 1</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:55"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:55"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>2</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:56"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:56"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>3</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:57"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:57"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>4</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:58"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:58"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>5</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:59"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:59"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>6</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:60"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:60"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>7</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:61"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:61"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>8</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:62"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:62"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>9</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:63"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:63"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>10</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:64"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:64"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>11</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:65"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:65"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>12</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:66"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:66"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>13</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:67"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:67"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>14</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:68"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:68"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>15</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:69"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:69"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>16</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:70"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:70"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>17</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:71"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:71"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>18</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:72"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:72"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>19</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:73"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:73"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>20</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:74"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:74"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>21</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:75"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:75"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>22</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:76"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:76"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>23</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:77"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:77"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>24</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:78"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:78"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>25</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:79"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:79"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>26</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:80"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:80"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>27</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:81"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:81"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>28</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:82"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:82"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>29</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:83"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:83"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>30</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:84"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:84"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>31</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:85"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:85"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>32</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:86"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:86"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>33</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:87"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:87"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>34</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:88"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:88"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>35</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:89"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:89"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>36</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:90"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:90"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>37</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:91"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:91"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>38</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:92"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:92"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>39</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:93"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:93"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>40</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:94"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:94"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>41</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:95"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:95"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>42</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:96"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:96"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>43</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <div xml:lang="eng" type="version">
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:97"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:97"/>
               <head>BRIEF INSTRVC<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION VPON THE CONTREFAIC TINGES, CONCERNING THE RIGHT VSE, OF ALL vvhat a Souldier needeth to knovv in handling of the Pike, for the yonge or vntrayned Souldier, vvhich inſtruction agreeth by nomber vvith every figure in order.</head>
               <head type="sub">PIKEMEN.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the vſing of the Pike is firſt ſhevved vnto the Souldier hovv he (ſtanding ſtill) ſhall hold the Pike before him, gouerne it againſt the thumbe and take it vp in three tymes, That is to ſaye: he ſhall not (for comelynes) ſet it vvith in or vvithout the right foote, but iuſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him in the ſame line: vvell vnderſtanding that he is not bound to ſet the right foote alvvayes before. His arme he ſhall hold not ſtretcht out butt a little bended and his hand about the height of his eyes.</p>
               <p>In the 2. figure is ſhevved, hovv, before the firſt changeinge of his holde, he ſhall vvith the right hand lift the Pike a little from the ground and take it ſodainely againe vvith the left hand tovvardes the neather ende, leavinge ſo much lengthe belovve as he can afftervvardes reatch vvell vvith the right hand, like as this figure doth teatche.</p>
               <p>In the 3. hovv he, before the ſecond changeinge of hold, ſhall lift vp the Pike vvith the left hand and quickely vvith the right hand take the ſame at the ende.</p>
               <p>In the 4. hovv, before the third changeinge of hold, (having ioyned the Pike vvith the left hand againſt the right arme) he ſhall gouerne the ſame againſt the ſayde arme and carry it vp, or advanced.</p>
               <p>In the 5. hovv (havinge carried the Pike advanced) he ſhall ſet the ſame dovvne vpon the ground againe in three tymes, like as before, that is: he ſhall let the right hand vvith the Pike ſinke a little together, and for the firſt changeinge of handes, vvith the left hand take the ſame vpvvards, like as this figure teatchet.</p>
               <p>In the 6. hovv, to change the ſecond hold, he ſhall let the Pike ſinke vvith the left hand and vvith the right hand quickely take the ſame heigher, like as this figure ſhevveth.</p>
               <p>In the 7. hovv, at the third changeinge of holde, he ſhall gouerne the Pike vvith the right hand onely and ſet it againe vpon the ground, as is taught in the firſt figure, and if he vvill then laye the Pike vpon the ſhoulder, he ſhall doe that againe in three tymes, as follovveth.</p>
               <p>In the 8 place is ſhevved, hovv, before the firſt changeinge of holde (havinge the Pike in the right hand) he ſhall let the ſame fall ouer a little againſt the thumbe and preſently take it vvith the left hand cloſe to the right hand, like as this figure ſhevveth.</p>
               <p>In the 9. hovv he (before the ſecond changeinge of hold) ſhall bringe the Pike forevvard vvith the left hand and vvith the right hand take hold backvvard, the more handſomely and gracefully to lay the Pike on the ſhoulder.</p>
               <p>In the 10. hovv he (in the third changeinge of hold) ſhall carye the Pike levell vpon the ſhoulder, hold the right arme vp and the thumbe againſt the pike, not onely for faſhions ſake, but becauſe he maye gouerne and carye the ſame the better.</p>
               <p>In the 11. hovv he ſhall carye the Pike ſlopinghe to avoyd the danger of hurting on an other vvhen they marche cloſe: and in the next figure ſhall beſhevved hovv he (carrying the Pike levell or ſlopinge) ſhall let the ſame ſinke vvhen ſoever he vvill come to porte or othervvayes charge the pike, and hovv he ſhall ſet the ſame at three tymes againe vpon the ground, and deſiring to laye the ſame vpon the ſhoulder, ſhall doe it at three tymes, as is taught before, But vvhen he carrieth the Pike advanced he ſhall charge the ſame at one tyme.</p>
               <p>In the 12. hovv he (before the firſt changeinge of hold) ſhall take the Pike vvith the left hand ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dely as farr as he (ſtandinge right) can reatch, liftinge the ſame vvith the left hand vp from the ſhoulder, the better and vvith more eaſe to be able to caſt the Pike ouer vvith the ſharp ende before.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:98"/>
In the 13. hovv he (before the ſecond remoovinge of his hand) having brought the Pike vvith the ſharpe end before, ſhall take the ſame vvith the right hand vnder at the end and lettinge it ſinke handſomely dovvnevvards, ſhall ſo the more conveniently paſſe through the porte.</p>
               <p>In the 14. hovv he (at the thirde tyme) ſhall duely charge the Pike, the right arme ſtretcht out, havinge the ſame vvell in the right hand, ſetting the left elbovve faſt againſt the hippe, and ſhall be taught hovv he ſhall ſet dovvne the Pike againe at three tymes or motions.</p>
               <p>In the 15. hovv he (before the firſt changeinge of hands) vvith his right hand ſhall put dovvne the butt ende of the Pike, the better and more eaſelye to rayſe the ſharp end of the ſame.</p>
               <p>In the 16. hovv he (before the ſecond changeinge of hand) ſhall take holde of the Pike vvith the right hand (aboue the left) ſo farr as hee eaſely can reache.</p>
               <p>In the 17. hovv he ſhall at the thirde tyme, ſett the Pike dovvne to the ground, guyde it againſt the thum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be, and hold the ſame vvell as is ſayd at the firſt figure, and ſhall in the tvvo next figures be ſhevved, hovv he carrying the Pike vp or advanced, ſhall charge the ſame at one tyme onely, but becauſe in the former figures is ſufficiently taught hovv he (the Pike ſtanding dovvne) ſhall take it vp againe, it ſhall therefore be needleſſe to demonſtrate it againe vvith the figures, but thus much ſhall ſerue onely for remembrance.</p>
               <p>In the 18. hovv, havinge at three times (as is ſufficiently ſayd heretofore) taken the Pike from the ground and the but end in his hand, he ſhall guyde and carrye the ſame advanced in the right hand againſt the ſame arme.</p>
               <p>In the 19. hovv he (havinge the Pike advanced) ſhall take the ſame vvith the left hand higher and at the ſame tyme charge vvithall, but if he deſire to ſet the Pike dovvne againe, he ſhall doe it as is taught by the figures before. But if (having charged the Pike) he vvould carrye the ſame againe advanced, he ſhall doe it in one poſture or motion.</p>
               <p>In the 20. hovv (ſtanding at a porte at the marchinge in or out of any men) he ſhall hold the Pike at the point like as this figure ſhevveth.</p>
               <p>In the 21. hovv he (trayling the Pike) ſhall hold the ſame cloſe at the point and ſet the right hand aboue the hippe faſt to the bodye, and if he vvill charge or other vvayes carrye the ſame, then he muſt (as it vvere) meaſure the Pike by palmes, handling it vvith convenient diſtance, like as the tvvo next follovving figures ſhall ſhevv.</p>
               <p>In the 22. hovv (before the firſt changeinge of hands havinge firſt ſo farr as he could put forvvard the Pike vvith the right hand) he ſhall (bendinge him ſelf a little) palme or hand-on the ſame ſpeedely, takinge it ſtill from beneath or belovve.</p>
               <p>In the 23. hovv he (palminge forvvard) ſhall bringe the Pike vvith the left hand yet more forvvard, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinge brought the right hand vvhich vvas the foremoſt before, to be novv behynde vpon the ſecond chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge of the hande.</p>
               <p>In the 24. hovv (havinge brought the Pike (by palminge) forvvard to the end and having the ſame ſure in his hand) he ſhall charge the ſame: but if he vvould in the former manner (that is traylinge) carry the ſayd Pike, lett (hym by the ſayd manner of palminge) bring the ſame backvvard againe. Here is to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered that (although there be but tvvo palminge figures here ſet dovvne, vvhich ſome might take as if it vvere ſayd that iuſt in three remooves of the hande the Pike could be charged yet is not that our meaninge, but that follovving the example of thoſe tvvo palming figures, the learner muſt knovv that he is to palme or hand the Pike (by ſhifting hands) ſo long till he haue recouered the lovver or butt end of the Pike into his right hand.</p>
               <p>In the 25. hovv he (expectingt horſemen) ſhall ſet the Pike againſt the right foote and dravv his ſvvord ouer the left arme, like as this figure ſhevveth.</p>
               <p>In the 26. hovv, marchinge vvith the Pike vpon the ſhoulder, he ſhall conveniently turne hym ſelf to the left hand (if need be) and charge the Pike backvvard in three motions or remooues of the hand.</p>
               <p>In the 27. hovv he (before the firſt changeinge his hold or remooue of his hand hauinge firſt vvith the right hand advanced the Pike from the ſhoulder) ſhall at the ſame tyme take hold of it ſome vvhat fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvard vvith the left hand, becauſe in ſo doinge he maye more eaſely lifte the Pike ouer his head.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:98"/>
In the 28. hovv (havinge the Pike ouer the head in the left hand and already turned hym ſelfe to the left ſide) he ſhall (for the ſecond remooving of hold) take the ſame vvith the right hand vnder at the end.</p>
               <p>In the 29. hovv (as is ſayd before) he ſhall the thirde tyme charge the Pike backvvard and ſtand turned about. The three follovvinge figures ſhall ſhevve hovv he ſhall turne him ſelfe in three motions, and alſo hovv he ſhall ſtand or marche, like as is ſeene in the 26. figure.</p>
               <p>In the 30. hovv he (before the firſt remoovinge of the hand) ſhall reach and take the Pike farther vvith the left hand and prepare him ſelfe to turne.</p>
               <p>In the 31. hovv (having already turned hym ſelfe to the right ſide) he ſhall lift the Pike ouer his head vvith the left hand and receaue or take the ſame ſomevvhat more backvvard vvith the right hand.</p>
               <p>In the 32. hovv he (for the thirde tyme) ſhall carry the Pike againe in the right hand vpon the ſhoulder ſloped, leuell or advanced, if need be.</p>
               <p>And ſeeing experience teatcheth, that the ſouldier can not ſpeedely nor hanſomely change the ordre of his Pike, but through knovvledge hovv to handle and hold the ſame vvell, therefore are there, for his better inſtruction, certayne vvords of command hereby annexed together vvith the tymes of chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geinge or remoovinge of the hands, vvhich doe altogether agree both vvith the rules of inſtruction, as alſo vvith the Cypher numbers alloted to ech ſeuerall picture, to the ende that the Captaynes may ſhevv or theatch theyr neevv vntrayned Souldiers the handlinge of the Pike after this manner, I meane ſo much as is neceſſary for theyr vſe, but havinge once obtayned the handling, the Souldier ſhall be then exerciſed vvith the vvords of command onely, vvich vvords are ſet here after apart and vvithout the diſtinctions of tymes, ſuch as here immediatly follovv.</p>
               <list>
                  <head>The vvords of Command. VVith the tyme of changeing of holde.</head>
                  <item>1. Your Pike ſtanding dovvne advaunce in three tymes or motions.</item>
                  <item>2. the firſt Tyme or Motion.</item>
                  <item>3. the ſecond
Tyme or Motion.</item>
                  <item>4. the thirde Tyme or Motion.</item>
                  <item>5. Order your Pike. the firſt Motion.</item>
                  <item>6. Order your Pike. ſecond
Motion.</item>
                  <item>7. Order your Pike. thirde Motion.</item>
                  <item>8. Shoulder your Pike and carrye it levell. the firſt Tyme.</item>
                  <item>9. Shoulder your Pike and carrye it levell. ſecond Tyme.</item>
                  <item>10. Shoulder your Pike and carrye it levell. thirde Tyme.</item>
                  <item>11. Slope your Pike.</item>
                  <item>12. Porte your Pike. the firſt  Tyme.</item>
                  <item>13. Porte your Pike. ſecond
  Tyme.</item>
                  <item>14. Porte your Pike. thirde  Tyme.</item>
                  <item>15. Order your Pike. the firſt Motion.</item>
                  <item>16. Order your Pike. ſecond
Motion.</item>
                  <item>17. Order your Pike. thirde Motion.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Advance your Pike in three Tymes or Motions.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:22852:99" rendition="simple:additions"/>
18. Theſe three haue but one figure marked vvith the number 18. becauſe the other tvvo are ſhevved before.</item>
                  <item>19. Charge your Pike in one motion.</item>
                  <item>20. Cheeke your Pike.</item>
                  <item>21. Trayle your Pike.</item>
               </list>
               <p>And palming your Pike charge.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>22. Not bound to doe this in three motions,</item>
                  <item>23. or tymes, as is ſayd in the inſtruction</item>
                  <item>24. numero 24.</item>
                  <item>25. Charge your Pike at the right foote and dravv your ſvvord.</item>
                  <item>26. Your Pike being ſhouldered charge backvvard in three tymes.</item>
                  <item>27. the firſt Tyme.</item>
                  <item>28. ſecond
Tyme.</item>
                  <item>29. thirde Tyme.</item>
                  <item>30. Right to your order and your Pike ſlope. the firſt Motion.</item>
                  <item>31. Right to your order and your Pike ſlope. ſecond
Motion.</item>
                  <item>32. Right to your order and your Pike ſlope. thirde Motion.</item>
               </list>
               <p>The vvords of command in generall, after vvhich the Captaynes ſhall ſee theyr Souldiers exerciſed vvhen the Souldier is come ſo far that he can handle his Pike as becommeth, it is then to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood that for orders ſake theſe vvords follovvinge (ſo farr as is needfull) are ſet dovvne agreeinge to the former vvhich haue theyr reference to the Pikemen, exceptinge ſome only vvhich in the order of the Pike doe the ſame action that hath bene ſhevved inough by the figures vvith theyr tymes or motions. Alſo that at the firſt command, vvhere is ſayd advaunce your Pike, it is ſpoken to the firſt figure, that ſtandeth ſtill in order vvith his Pike ſett dovvne, and the better to prevent all confuſion, muſt be remembred that euery manner of carryinge or charginge of the Pike muſt be done apart, and no other begonne or taken in hand till the firſt be done and the Pike ſet dovvne in order againe. To vvhich purpoſe this generall command ſhall be vſed or obſerved.</p>
               <p>Order your Pike.</p>
               <list>
                  <head>Words of Command. VVith out theyr tyme of changeinge holde.</head>
                  <item>Advaunce your Pike.</item>
                  <item>Set dovvne your Pike.</item>
                  <item>Shoulder your Pike.</item>
                  <item>Leuell your Pike.</item>
                  <item>Slope your Pike.</item>
                  <item>Porte your Pike.</item>
                  <item>Order your pike.</item>
                  <item>Advaunce your pike.</item>
                  <item>Charge your pike.</item>
                  <item>Order your pike.</item>
                  <item>Cheeke your pike.</item>
                  <item>Order your pike.</item>
                  <item>Trayle your pike.</item>
                  <item>Charge your pike.</item>
                  <item>Order your pike.</item>
                  <item>Charge your pike againſt the right foote and dravv your ſvvord</item>
                  <item>Order your pike.</item>
                  <item>Shoulder your pike.</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:22852:99"/>
Charge your pike backvvard.</item>
                  <item>Right to your firſt order.</item>
                  <item>Slope your pike.</item>
               </list>
               <p>And although theſe vvords of commannd follovve after this manner becauſe the Pike muſt alvvayes be ſett dovvne againe, vvhere by is thought that the Souldiers cann the ſooner learne the perfect or faſt handlinge of the ſame, yet is not the meaning that a man ſhould be juſt bound to it alone, but he maye aſvvell beginne at the middeſt or any other place, as vvell as at the beginninge to doe the Comands, and that as occaſion ſerueth, vvhich ſtandes in the diſcretion of the expert Captayne or Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandour.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>WITH PRIVILEDGE OF THE EMPEROVRS MA<hi rend="sup">TYE</hi>. THE FRENCH KINGES, AND THE LORDS ESTATES of the Vnited Provinces &amp;c.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>VVhere of the contence is ſuch.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>NO man of vvhat qualitie or cöndition ſoeuer he be, ſhall vndertake to contrefaict this preſent bocke of the exerciſe of Armes, or any vvhere els contrefaited-ſell the ſame, vvith in theyr Empire Kingdome or Landes, in the tyme of eighr yeares follovvinge, be it in ſmall or great, in parte or vvhole, neither the vvritinges nor the figures, nor the order kept in this vvorke, any vvayes to follovve vvithout expreſſe conſent or leaue of Iacob de Gheyn vpon payne of loſſe of all the contrefaict vvorke, and threeſcore pound ſterling beſides, as more plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nely is to ſene in the principall letters giue here of vnto him, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A remembrance for the Bookebindere.</head>
                  <p>THe vvritinges are (as alſo the figures) dealt af in three ſundry partes, as Calivres, Muſkets and Pikes, änd ſhall be bound-in after this faſhion: The vvrytinges of the Calivres before the figures of the ſame, and the other vvritinges likevviſe, eche before theyr ovvne figures.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="dut" type="version">
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:100"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:100"/>
               <head>CORTE ONDER VVYSINGHE OP DE FIGVERLIICKE AFBEELDINGHE, BELANGHENDE t'recht ghebruyck, van al t'ghene een Soldaet int handelen vande Spies noodich is, voor dejonghe ofte onervaren Soldaten, vvclcke ondervvijſinghe by'tghetal op elcke figure vervolghens is correſponderende.</head>
               <head type="sub">SPIES-DRAGHER.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Ntexerceren vande Spies vvort den Soldaet eerſtelijcken ghevveſen, hoe hy ſtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaende in ordeninghe de Spies voor ſich vvel houden ende teghens den duym regeren, ende in dry tijden opvvaerts draghen ſal, als te vveten hy en ſal de Spies, vvelſtaens halven binnen noch buyten den rechter voet ſetten, maer ghenoechſaem op de ſelfde linie, ſonder nochtans dat hy ghchouden ſy den rechter voet int ſtilſtaen altijt voor teſtellen, den arm niet vvtghe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrect maer een vveynich gheboghen, ende de hant ſoo hooch alſt gheſicht houden.</p>
               <p>Ten 2. hoe hy voor de eerſte hervattinghe, de Spies met de rechter hant een vveynich vander aerden om hooch heffen ſal, ende met eenen de ſelfde verdichlijck (met de lincker hant) nedervvaerts aen vatten, latende ſoo veel lencktc beneden, als hy hier naer met de rechter hant ſal connen bereycken, ghelijck deſe figuere bevvijſt.</p>
               <p>Ten 3. hoe hy voor de tvveede hervattinghe de Spies met de lincker handt om hooch heffen, ende met de rechter de ſelfde onder aent eynde (verdichlijcken) vatten ſal.</p>
               <p>Ten 4. hoe hy voor de derde hervattinghe, hebbende de Spies met de lincker hant teghens den rechter arm ghevoecht, de ſelfde inde rechter hant teghens den ſelfden arm regieren ende opvvaerts draghen ſal.</p>
               <p>Ten 5. hoe hy hebbende den Spies opvvaerts gedrage<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, de ſelfde vveder in dry tijden als vore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, op der aerden neder ſetten ſal, als te vveten hy ſal de rechter hant met de Spies t'ſamen een vveynich laten ſincken, ende de ſelfde met de lincker hant, voor de eerſte hervattinghe, opvvaerts aenvatten, ghelijck deſe figure bevvijſt.</p>
               <p>Ten 6. hoe hy om de tvveede hervattinghe te doen, de Spies met de lincker hant ſal laten ſincken, ende met de rechter hant de ſelfde (met eenen) verdichlijck hoogher vatten, ghelijck deſe figure bevvijſt.</p>
               <p>Ten 7. hoe hy inde derde hervattinghe de Spies met de rechter hant alleen regeren, ende vveder als byde eerſte figure gheſeyt is, op der aerden nederſetten ſal, ende vvillende als dan de Spies op ſchouder legghen ſalt ſelfde vveder in drytijden gheſchieden, als volghen ſal.</p>
               <p>Ten 8 hoe hy voor de eerſte hervattinghe de Spies inde rechterhant hebbende de ſelfde tegens den duym een vveynich ſal laten overvallen, ende met eenen verdichlijck de ſelfde met de linckerhant dicht onder de rechter aenvatten, ghelijck deſe figure bevvijſt.</p>
               <p>Ten 9. hoe hy voor de tvveede hervattinghe de Spies met de lincker hant naer voren brenghen, ende met de rechter handt de ſelfde achtervvaerts aenvatten ſal, om de Spies alſoo bequaemlijck op de ſchouder te legghen.</p>
               <p>Ten 10. hoe hy inde derde hervattinghe de Spies op de ſchouder plat dragen, den rechter arm om hooch, ende den duym teghen de Spies houden ſal, ten eynde hct niet alleen vvel en ſtae, maer dat hy de ſelfde dies te beter regieren ende draghen can.</p>
               <p>Ten 11. hoe hy de Spies ſchuyns draghen ſal, om vvanneermen dicht op een Marcheert d'een den ande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren (met het punt) niet en ſoude beſchadighen, ende ſalinde naervolghende figuren ghevveſen vvorden hoe hy, draghende de Spies ſchuyns ofte plat, de ſelfde in dry tyden ſal laten ſincken, vvanneer hy de Spies door een Poort ofte anderſins vellen vvil, ende hoe hy in dry tijden de ſelfde vvederom op der aerden nederſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſal, ende vvillende de ſelfde op de ſchouderlegghen, ſal t'ſelve (alſt te voren ghevveſen is) oock in dry tijden gheſchieden. Maer ſoo vvanneer hy de Spies opvvaerts draghet, ſoo ſal hy die alleenlijck in een tijt vellen, ende daer naer vvederom in een tijt opvvaerts dragen.</p>
               <p>Ten 12. hoe hy voorde eerſte hervattinghe de Spies met de lincker hant ſoo verde hy de ſelfde, recht ſtaende can bereycken verdichlijcken aenvatten ſal, heffende de ſelfde met de rechter hant ghelijckelijck
<pb facs="tcp:22852:101"/>
vande ſchouder om hooch, om alſoo bequamelijck de Spies met de punt voorvvaerts over te vvorpen.</p>
               <p>Ten 13. hoe hy voorde tvveede hervattinghe de Spies (hebbende de ſelfde alreede met de punt naer voren ghebrocht) met de rechter hant onder aent eynde vatten ſal, ende de ſelfde van boven nedervvaerts bequa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melijcken laten ſincken, om alſoo door de poort te connen paſſeren.</p>
               <p>Ten 14. hoe hy ten derde mael de Spies bequamelijcken vellen, den rechter arm uyt gheſtreckt, de Spies inde ſelfde hant vvel vatten, ende den lincker ellenbooch teghen de heupe vaſt ſetten ſal, ende ſal voorder ghevveſen vvorden hoe hy in dry tijden de Spies vveder neder ſetten ſal.</p>
               <p>Ten 15. hoe hy voor de eerſte hervattinghe de Spies met de rechter hant, achter om leech drucken ſal, om alſoo bequamelijck de ſelfde voor om hooch tedoen rijſen.</p>
               <p>Ten 16. hoe hy voor de tvveede hervattinghe de Spies met de rechter hant (boven de lincker) ſoo verde hy de ſelfde ghemackelijck bereycken can, aenvatten ſal.</p>
               <p>Ten 17. hoe hy ten derde mael de Spies vveder op der aerden nederſetten, ende teghens den duym regie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren, ende vvel houden ſal, ghelijck byde cerſte figure gheſeyt is, ende ſal inde tvvee naervolghende figuren ghevveſen vvorden hoe hy de Spies opvvaerts draghende, de ſelfde alleen in een tijt vellen ſal, dan alſoo inde voorgaende figuren ghenoech ghevveſen is, hoe hy de Spies nederſtaende in dry tijden opvvaerts draghen ſal, ſoo heeftmen ſulckx hier onnoodich gheacht met figuren meer te vvijſen, maer ſtellen dit alleen tot memorie.</p>
               <p>Ten 18. hoe hy hebbende de Spies in dry tijden (ghelijck hier voren ghenoech ghevveſen is) vander aer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den opgheheven ende onder aent eynde ghevat, de ſelfde inde rechter hant teghens den ſelfden arm regieren, ende opvvaerts draghen ſal.</p>
               <p>Ten 19. hoe hy hebbende de Spies opvvaerts ghedraghen, de ſelfde met de lincker hant hoogher aenvat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, ende in een tijt vellen ſal, ende vvillende de Spies vveder nederſtellen ſalt ſelfde gheſchieden alſt byde vorighe figuren ghevveſen is, maer indien hy de Spies ghevelt hebbende vveder vvilde opvvaerts draghen, ſalt ſelfde alleen in een tijt gheſchieden.</p>
               <p>Ten 20. hoe hy ſtaende aen een poort (int vvt oft in trecken van eenich volck) de Spies aent punt houden ſal, ghelijck deſe figure bevvijſt.</p>
               <p>Ten 21. hoe hy de Spies ſleypende draghen, de ſelfde dicht by de punt vatten, ende de hant recht boven de heupe vaſt teghens het lijf aenſetten ſal, ende vvillende de ſelfde vellen oft op een ander vvijſe draghen, ſoo moet het ſelfde door palmen gheſchieden ghelijck de tvvee naervolghende figuren vvijſen ſullen.</p>
               <p>Ten 22. hoe hy voor de eerſte hervattinghe, hebbende eerſt de Spies ſoo verde hy heeft gheconnen, met de rechter hant, voor uyt gheſchoten, de ſelfde met de lincker hant, een vveynich boeckende, ondervvaerts verdichlijck aen palmen ſal.</p>
               <p>Ten 23. hoe hy voorts palmende, de Spies met de lincker hant noch meer naer voor brenghen ſal, heb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bende de rechter die te voren de voorſte vvas, alreede hervat, ende als nu achter ghebracht.</p>
               <p>Ten 24. hoe hy hebbende de Spies al palmende voor ghebrocht ende vvel ghevat, de ſelfde vellen ſal, maer indien hy de Spies vveder op de voorgaende vvijſe (te vveten ſleypende) draghen vvou, ſoo moet hy de ſelfde palmende vveder naer achter brengen, is mede te bemercken (dat al iſt ſoo) datmen hier maer tvvee palmende figuren en heeft gheſtelt, vvaer uyt eenighe ſouden moghen verſtaen als oftmen ſegghen vvilde datmen de Spies palmende iuſt in dry tijden ſoude connen vellen, t'ſelfde nochtans de meyninghe niet<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> en is, maer datmen op de voorgaende maniere uytvvijſende de tvvee palmende figuren, de Spies ſoo menich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mael haer palmen moet, tot datmen de ſelfde met de rechter hant onder aent eynde ghevat heeft.</p>
               <p>Ten 25. hoe hy Ruyter vervvachtende de Spies teghen de rechter voet ſetten, ende met een zijn gevveer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> buyten den lincker arm uyt trecken ſal, ghelijck de figure bevvijſt.</p>
               <p>Ten 26. hoe hy Marcherende met de Spies op ſchouder, ſich ſelven alſt van noode ſy, bequamelijck naer de lincker hant omvvenden, ende de Spies in dry tijden achtervvaert vellen ſal.</p>
               <p>Ten 27. hoe hy voor de eerſte hervattinghe, hebbende de Spies eerſt met de rechterhant vande ſchouder om hooch geheven, de ſelfde gelijckelijck met de lincker hant voorvvaerts aenvatten ſal, om ſoo doende de Spies bequamelijck over thooft te heffen.</p>
               <p>Ten 28. hoe hy hebbende de Spies over thooft inde lincker hant, mits hem ſelven alreede naer de linc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker
<pb facs="tcp:22852:101"/>
zijde ghekeert hebbende, de ſelfde met de rechter hant aent eynde (voor de tvveede hervattinghe) vat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſal.</p>
               <p>Ten 29. hoe hy de Spies ghelijck gheſeyt is, ten derdemael achtervvaerts vellen, ende gans ghekeert ſtaen ſal, ende ſullen de dry naervolghende figuren vvijſen, hoe hy in dry tijden ſich ſelven vvederom kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren, ende ghelijck de 26. figure ſtaen ofte Marcheren <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>al.</p>
               <p>Ten 30, hoe hy voor d'eerſte hervattinghe de Spies met de lincker hant verde<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bereycken ende aenvat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, oock ſich ſelven tot vveder om keeren ghereet maecken ſal.</p>
               <p>Ten 31. hoe hy hebbende ſich ſelven alreede naer de rechte <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ijde omghekeert, de Spies met de lincker hant over het hooft heffen, ende de ſelfde vvat achtervvaerts, inde rechter hant ontfanghen ende aenvatten ſal.</p>
               <p>Ten 32. hoe hy ten derde mael de Spies vveder inde rechter hant op de ſchouder ſchuyns ofte plat dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghen ſal, oft oock opvvaerts indient van noode ſy.</p>
               <p>Ende alſoo bevonden vvort dat den Soldaet zijn Spies niet vvel noch verdichlijck en can herſtellen, dan door vvetenſchap vande ſelfde vvel te connen handelen ende hervatten, ſoo zijn tot onder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvijs vanden ſelfden hier by gheordineert, ſeeckere vvoorden van bevele met hun tijden van hervattinghe die al te ſamen met ghetal op de figuren als oock op d'onderrechtinghe vervolghens zijn correſponderen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, op dat de Capiteynen h<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n nieuvve ende o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erva<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en Soldaten, op deſe maniere het handelen vande Spies, ſoo veel hun van noode is, moghen doen leeren, maer de handelinghe hebbende, ſullen de Soldaten gheoeffent vvorden achtervolghens de vvoorden van bevele, die hier naer alleen, ende ſonder tijden, op hun ſelven gheſtelt zijn.</p>
               <list>
                  <head>Devvoorden van bevele. Met hun tijden van hervattinghe.</head>
                  <item>1. V Spies neder ſtaende, in dry tijden opvvaerts draecht.</item>
                  <item>2. eerſten tijt.</item>
                  <item>3. tvveeden
tijt.</item>
                  <item>4. derden tijt.</item>
                  <item>5. V Spies herſtelt. eerſten tijt.</item>
                  <item>6. V Spies herſtelt. tvveeden
tijt.</item>
                  <item>7. V Spies herſtelt. derden tijt.</item>
                  <item>8. V Spies op de ſchouder leght ende plat draecht. eerſten tijt.</item>
                  <item>9. V Spies op de ſchouder leght ende plat draecht. tvveeden
tijt.</item>
                  <item>10. V Spies op de ſchouder leght ende plat draecht. derden tijt.</item>
                  <item>11. Schuyns u Spies draecht.</item>
                  <item>12. V Spies door de Poort velt. eerſten tijt.</item>
                  <item>13. V Spies door de Poort velt. tvveeden
tijt.</item>
                  <item>14. V Spies door de Poort velt. derden tijt.</item>
                  <item>15. V Spies herſtelt. eerſten tijt.</item>
                  <item>16. V Spies herſtelt. tvveeden
tijt.</item>
                  <item>17. V Spies herſtelt. derden tijt.</item>
               </list>
               <p>V Spies in dry tijden opvvaerts draecht.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:22852:102"/>
18. Deſe dry tijden hebben maer een figuer geteyckent met numero achthie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> om dat d'ander <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> elen zijn.</item>
               </list>
               <p>V Spies in eenen tijt velt.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>19. Eenen tijt.</item>
                  <item>20. Aent punt u Spies hout.</item>
                  <item>21. V Spies ſleept.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Ende palmende u Spies velt.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>22. Dit onghehouden in dry tijden te doen.</item>
                  <item>23. ghelijck byde onderrechtinge nume.</item>
                  <item>24. ro 24. gheſeyt vvort.</item>
                  <item>25. Teghen u rechter voet u Spies velt, ende u ghevveer treckt.</item>
                  <item>26. V Spies op de ſchouder legghende, in dry tijden achtervvaerts velt.</item>
                  <item>27. eerſten tijt.</item>
                  <item>28. tvveeden
tijt.</item>
                  <item>29. derden tijt.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Rechts herſtelt u, en u Spies ſchuyns draecht.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>30. eerſten tijt.</item>
                  <item>31. tvveeden
tijt.</item>
                  <item>32. derden tijt.</item>
               </list>
               <p>De vvoorden van bevele, vvaer naer de Cappiteynen hun Soldaten ſullen doen oeffenen, vvanneer ſy ſoo verde zijn, dat ſy de Spies connen handelen, men ſal verſtaen datmen om ordre te hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den deſe vvoorden ſoo veel noodich is, oock op de figueren heeft doen vervolghen, uytgheſondert eenige <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> herſtellen vande Spies t'ſelfde vverck doen, dat te voren by de figuren met hun tijden ghenoech is ghevveſen, oock datmen int eerſte bevel, daermen ſeght opvvaerts u Spies draecht, ſpreeckt teghens de eer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte figure, die met zijn Spies nedergheſtelt in ordeninge ſtil ſtaet. Ende om alle confuſie te mijden ſtaet te mercken dat ieder maniere vande Spies te draghen (oft oock te vellen) beſonder ende alleen ghedaen, ende gheen ander aenghevanghen moet vverden al voor t'eerſte volbracht, ende de Spies vveder nederghe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtelt ſy, ten vvelcken eynde men dit generael commandement ghebruycken ſal.</p>
               <p>V Spies herſtelt.</p>
               <list>
                  <head>Woorden van bevele. Sonder hun tijden van hervattinghe.</head>
                  <item>Opvvaerts u Spies draecht.</item>
                  <item>Neder u Spies ſtelt.</item>
                  <item>Op de ſchouder u Spies leght.</item>
                  <item>Plat u Spies draecht.</item>
                  <item>Schuyns u Spies draecht.</item>
                  <item>Door de Poort u Spies velt.</item>
                  <item>Neder u Spies ſtelt.</item>
                  <item>Opvvaerts u Spies draecht.</item>
                  <item>V Spies velt.</item>
                  <item>Neder u Spies ſtelt.</item>
                  <item>Aent punt u Spies hout.</item>
                  <item>Neder u Spies ſtelt.</item>
                  <item>V Spies ſleept.</item>
                  <item>V Spies velt.</item>
                  <item>Neder u Spies ſtelt.</item>
                  <item>Teghen u rechter voet u Spies velt, ende u ghevveer treckt.</item>
                  <item>Neder u Spies ſtelt.</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:22852:102"/>
Op de ſchouder u Spies leght.</item>
                  <item>Achtervvaerts u Spies velt.</item>
                  <item>Rechts herſtelt u.</item>
                  <item>Schuyns u Spies draecht.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Ende al iſt ſoo dat deſe beuel vvoorden aldus achter den anderen vervolghen, om datmen de Spies t'elckemael vveder herſtellen moet, vvaer door men acht dat de Soldaten de vaſte handelinghe der ſelver te eerder connen leeren, ſoo en is nochtans de meeninghe niet datmen hier aen ſoo vaſt ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bonden ſy, oft men mach ooc vvel beginnen vvt den midden, oft anders (ſoo vvel als van voren) deſe beve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len te doen, ende dat naer gheleghentheyt vander ſaecke, het vvelck ſtaet ter diſcretie vanden ervaren Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piteyn oft bevelhebber.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>MET PREVILEGIE VANDE KEY: MA: DEN KONINC VAN VRANCRIICK, EN DE E. M. HEEREN Staten Generael der Vereenichde Nederlanden.</head>
                  <p>Ende is den inhout aldus luydende.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>DAt niemant hem en vervoordere t'ſy van wat qualiteyt ofte conditie by ſy, dit teghen woordich boeck van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de VVapenhande linghe naer te maecken, oft elders naer ghemaeckt binnen haere Rijcken ende landen te vercoopen, binnen den tijt van acht naervolghende laren, t'ſy int cleyn ofte int groot, int deel ofte int gheheel, de ſchriften noch oock de figueren, oock de ordre in dit werck ghehouden gheenſins naer te volghen, ſonder expres conſent van Iacob de Geyn op verbeurte van allen het naer ghemaeckte werck, ende ſes hondert Carolus gulden daer en boven, als breeder blijckt by de principale brieven hem hier van ghegheven, &amp;c. Anno 1607.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>TOT MEMORIE VANDFN BOECK-BINDER.</head>
                  <p>DE ſchriften zijn (ghelijck oock de figueren) in dry beſondere deelen afghedeelt, als Roers, Muſquetten ende Spieſſen, ende ſullen inghebonden vvorden op deſe manier, te vveten, de ſchriften vande Roers voor de figuren der ſelve, ende de ander ſchriften van ghelijcken elckx voor hun eyghen figueren, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="illustrations">
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:103"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:103"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>IDGheÿn. in, 1</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:104"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:104"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>2</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:105"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:105"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>3</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:106"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:106"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>4</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:107"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:107"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>5</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:108"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:108"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>6</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:109"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:109"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>7</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:110"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:110"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>8</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:111"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:111"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>9</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:112"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:112"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>10</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:113"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:113"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>11</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:114"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:114"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>12</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:115"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:115"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>13</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:116"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:116"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>14</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:117"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:117"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>15</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:118"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:118"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>16</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:119"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:119"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>17</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:120"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:120"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>18</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:121"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:121"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>19</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:122"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:122"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>20</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:123"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:123"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>21</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:124"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:124"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>22</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:125"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:125"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>23</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:126"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:126"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>24</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:127"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:127"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>25</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:128"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:128"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>26</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:129"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:129"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>27</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:130"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:130"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>28</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:131"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:131"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>29</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:132"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:132"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>30</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:133"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:133"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>31</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:134"/>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22852:134"/>
                  <figure>
                     <head>32</head>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:135"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:22852:135"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
